{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The condition that causes vapour locking in a brake system is", "opta": "overheating of the fluid due to frequent brake application", "optb": "overcooling of the brakes during high speed driving", "optc": "keeping the vehicle without use for an extended period", "optd": "an excessively high engine speed on a downhill road", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The portion of a crankshaft which rests on cylinder block is called main journal.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A baffle plate is fitted inside the oil pan to prevent the oil from splashing when it is subjected to vibration and other movement during vehicle operation.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The motion of the cam is transferred to the valves through", "opta": "pistons", "optb": "rocker arms", "optc": "camshaft pulley", "optd": "valve stems", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following symptom is caused as a result of brake disc run out ?", "opta": "Ineffectiveness of the brakes", "optb": "Judder during braking", "optc": "Localized wearing of the brake pads", "optd": "Rapid wearing of the brake pads", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the engine coolant leaks into the engine oil, then engine oil", "opta": "appears milky", "optb": "becomes foamy", "optc": "turns black", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of an alternator in an automobile is to", "opta": "supply electric power", "optb": "convert mechanical energy into electrical energy", "optc": "continually recharge the battery", "optd": "partly convert engine power into electric power", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A clutch is usually designed to transmit maximum torque which is", "opta": "equal to the maximum engine torque", "optb": "80 per cent of the maximum engine torque", "optc": "150 per cent of the maximum engine torque", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What type of bearing is used for main bearings and connecting rod bearings ?", "opta": "Ballbearings", "optb": "Plain bearings", "optc": "Needle roller bearing", "optd": "Taper roller bearing", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is necessary to maintain the valve clearances as they", "opta": "reduce the resistance to sliding that occurs between the cam and the tappet", "optb": "allow for lengthening of the valves owing to the heat of combustion", "optc": "increase the speed at which the valves move up and down", "optd": "make the crankshaft turn smoothly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Incorrect steering axis inclination (S.A.I.) causes", "opta": "tendency to assume toe-out orientation", "optb": "generation of a braking effect at tight corners", "optc": "poor recovery of the steering wheel after making a turn", "optd": "the vehicle to pull to the side of lesser inclination", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a unit type body (frameless body) design, the sheet metal parts are welded together, forming a frame work to which outer skin is attached.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The torque available at the contact between driving wheels and road is known as", "opta": "brake effort", "optb": "tractive effort", "optc": "clutch effort", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A traction control system (TCS) in automobiles controls the", "opta": "vibrations on the steering wheel", "optb": "engine power during acceleration", "optc": "torque that is transmitted by the tyres to the road surface", "optd": "stopping distance in case of emergency", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In radial tyres", "opta": "one ply layer runs diagonally one way and another layer runs diagonally the other way", "optb": "all plies run parallel to one another and vertical to tyre bead", "optc": "inner tubes are always used", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The oil pump is driven by the", "opta": "camshaft", "optb": "alternator shaft", "optc": "crankshaft via drive belt", "optd": "crankshaft directly", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a spark plug, when the temperature of the central electrode exceeds a certain temperature, any carbon that has adhered will be burnt off, and the temperature at which this burning off carbon starts is referred to as the self cleaning temperature.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The flywheel and the pressure plate bind the clutch disc between them so that the engine and the transmission can be engaged.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The vehicle ride will be comfortable if", "opta": "unsprung mass is kept minimum", "optb": "sprang mass is kept minimum", "optc": "vehicle mass is kept minimum", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main function of intake manifold is that it", "opta": "promotes the mixture of air and fuel", "optb": "reduces intake noise", "optc": "cools the intake air to a suitable temperature", "optd": "distributes intake air equally to the cylinders", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Positive camber is used to compensate for wheels tilting inward due to the weight of the vehicle.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In automobiles G.V.W. refers to", "opta": "gross vehicle width", "optb": "gross vehicle weight", "optc": "gross vehicle wheel base", "optd": "gross vehicle wheel track", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The firing order for an in-line four cylinder I.C. engine is", "opta": "1-2-3-4", "optb": "1-3-4-2", "optc": "1-2-4-3", "optd": "1-3-2-4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a ventilated disc brake,", "opta": "a duct directs air towards the caliper for cooling while the vehicle is moving", "optb": "caliper is covered with cooling fins", "optc": "disc contains many small holes for optimum cooling performance", "optd": "disc contains radial vanes between its rubbing surfaces for optimum cooling performance", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effect of having excess camber is", "opta": "excessive steering alignment torque", "optb": "hard steering", "optc": "too much traction", "optd": "uneven tyre wear", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the air-fuel mixture in a spark ignition engine is too rich, then air-fuel ratio is about", "opta": "17:1", "optb": "15:1", "optc": "13:1", "optd": "10:1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The advantage of double-wishbone suspension design is that a large amount of freedom is available for setting geometry and precise settings can be made for driving comfort and steerability,", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The co-efficient of rolling resistance for a truck weighing 63 500 N is 0.018. The rolling resistance to the truck is", "opta": "1.143 N", "optb": "11.43 N", "optc": "114.3 N", "optd": "1143 N", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the level of tension in the belt is too high, it can result in a loss of power or in bending of the rotating shaft or crankshaft.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the air-fuel mixture ignites before the spark takes place at spark plug, the condition is called", "opta": "detonation", "optb": "ignition", "optc": "pre-ignition", "optd": "rumble", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The information provided by the oxygen (O2) sensor to the feedback control system is about the", "opta": "air-fuel ratio", "optb": "air temperature", "optc": "air flow speed", "optd": "exhaust gas volume", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diagram which shows the correct crank positions corresponding to the opening and closing of the valves, is known as", "opta": "indicator diagram", "optb": "axial force diagram", "optc": "valve timing diagram", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference between DOT 3 and DOT 4 brake fluids is", "opta": "DOT 4 fluid has a higher boiling point than DOT 3 fluid", "optb": "DOT 4 fluid has a lower boiling point than DOT 3 fluid", "optc": "DOT 3 and DOT 4 fluids have the same boiling point, but DOT 4 fluid has a longer service life", "optd": "DOT 4 fluid is more resistant to freezing than DOT 3 fluid", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The battery is an electrochemical device, which means battery", "opta": "makes chemicals by mechanical means", "optb": "uses chemical action to provide electricity", "optc": "has curved plates instead of flat plates", "optd": "does not use an electrolyte", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The operation of removing trapped air from the hydraulic braking system is known as", "opta": "trapping", "optb": "tapping", "optc": "bleeding", "optd": "cleaning", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The aluminium alloy is used in cylinder blocks because", "opta": "it is lighter and have good heat dissipation characteristics", "optb": "material cost is low", "optc": "it does not require any cylinder liners", "optd": "the piston is also made of aluminium alloy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a fuel injection system, the electronic control module (ECM) calculates the optimum fuel-injection volume for the engine condition based on the data received from the sensors, and injects this volume of fuel into the intake manifold at the optimum timing.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tilting of the front wheels away from the vertical, when viewed from the front of the car, is called", "opta": "camber", "optb": "caster", "optc": "toe-in", "optd": "toe-out", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main function of the tread pattern on tyre is that", "opta": "the tread grooves pass air between the tyre and road surface, thereby preventing tyre from overheating", "optb": "the crests between the tread grooves absorb road noise", "optc": "in wet conditions, the tread grooves expel water that is drawn between the tyre and road surface", "optd": "the tread pattern protects the tyre's inner carcass from small stones and pieces of glass", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compression ratio in petrol engine is kept less than in Diesel engine because", "opta": "it makes petrol engines lighter", "optb": "higher or equivalent compression ratio in petrol engines is not possible due to pre-ignition", "optc": "less compression ratio gives better performance", "optd": "it is just customary to have less compression ratio in petrol engines", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most commonly used supplementary restraint system (SRS) component is", "opta": "seat belt", "optb": "brake", "optc": "airbag", "optd": "steering", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The natural gas is compressed in a CNG cylinder at a pressure of", "opta": "200 bar", "optb": "220 bar", "optc": "250 bar", "optd": "300 bar", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cetane rating of Diesel fuel is in the order of", "opta": "25", "optb": "45", "optc": "70", "optd": "90", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The air gap between the central electrode and ground (or side) electrode of a spark plug is around", "opta": "0.2 mm", "optb": "0.5 mm", "optc": "1 mm", "optd": "1.5 mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cetane number of a Diesel fuel is a measure of", "opta": "volatility", "optb": "viscosity", "optc": "ignition quality", "optd": "delay peirod", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The valve overlap in four stroke petrol engines is approximately", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "60\u00b0", "optc": "90\u00b0", "optd": "120\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The petrol engines are also known as", "opta": "spark ignition (S.I.) engines", "optb": "compression ignition (C.I.) engines", "optc": "steam engines", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following indicates a multigrade oil ?", "opta": "SAE 30", "optb": "API SF", "optc": "SAE 20 W-50", "optd": "API 50", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of friction for the clutch facing is approximately", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "0.4", "optc": "0.8", "optd": "1.2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The component that connects the steering rack to the knuckles is", "opta": "tie-rod", "optb": "sector gear", "optc": "pivot", "optd": "spline", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four stage compressor, if the pressure at the first and third stage are 1 bar and 16 bar, then the delivery pressure at the fourth stage will be", "opta": "1 bar", "optb": "16 bar", "optc": "64 bar", "optd": "256 bar", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compressed air may be used", "opta": "in gas turbine plants", "optb": "for operating pneumatic drills", "optc": "in starting and supercharging of I.C. engines", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rocket works with maximum overall efficiency when air-craft velocity is __________ the jet velocity.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "one-half", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The volumetric efficiency for reciprocating air compressors is about", "opta": "10 to 40%", "optb": "40 to 60%", "optc": "60 to 70%", "optd": "70 to 90%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum temperature in a gas turbine is", "opta": "200\u00b0C", "optb": "500\u00b0C", "optc": "700\u00b0C", "optd": "1000\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rotary compressors are suitable for large discharge of air at low pressure.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stagnation pressure rise in a centrifugal compressor takes place", "opta": "in the diffuser only", "optb": "in the impeller only", "optc": "in the diffuser and impeller", "optd": "in the inlet guide vanes only", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total heat rejected in a reciprocating air compressor is equal to the sum of the heat rejected during polytropic compression per kg of air and heat rejected in the intercooler per kg of air.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a jet propulsion", "opta": "the propulsive matter is ejected from within the propelled body", "optb": "the propulsive matter is caused to flow around the propelled body", "optc": "its functioning does not depend upon presence of air", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An open cycle gas turbine works on the same cycle as that of a closed cycle gas turbine.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?", "opta": "In a two stage reciprocating air compressor with complete intercooling, maximum work is saved.", "optb": "The minimum work required for a two stage reciprocating air compressor is double the work required for each stage.", "optc": "The ratio of the volume of free air delivery per stroke to the swept volume of the piston is called volumetric efficiency.", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a single acting reciprocating compressor, the suction, compression and delivery of air takes place in __________ of the piston.", "opta": "one stroke", "optb": "two strokes", "optc": "three strokes", "optd": "four strokes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase in pressure in a vane blower takes place first due to compression and then due to back flow of air.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum delivery pressure in a rotary air compressor is", "opta": "10 bar", "optb": "20 bar", "optc": "30 bar", "optd": "50 bar", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a compressor is expressed in", "opta": "kg/m2", "optb": "kg/m3", "optc": "m3/min", "optd": "m3/kg", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in multi-stage compressors is done", "opta": "to cool the air during compression", "optb": "to cool the air at delivery", "optc": "to enable compression in two stages", "optd": "to minimise the work of compression", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a two stage reciprocating compressor, compression from p1 to p3 is with perfect intercooling and no pressure losses. If compression in both the cylinders follows the same polytropic process and the atmospheric pressure is pa, then the intermediate pressure p2 is given by", "opta": "p2 = (p1 + p3)/2", "optb": "p2 = p1.p3", "optc": "P2 = Pa x p3/p1", "optd": "p2 = pa p3/p1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of workdone per cycle to the stroke volume of the compressor is known as", "opta": "compressor capacity", "optb": "compression ratio", "optc": "compressor efficiency", "optd": "mean effective pressure", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The clearance volume in the compressor is kept minimum because it effects on volumetric efficiency.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The inlet pressure is always __________ the discharge pressure.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The ratio of the discharge pressure to the inlet pressure of air is called compressor efficiency.", "optb": "The compression ratio for the compressor is always greater than unity.", "optc": "The compressor capacity is the ratio of workdone per cycle to the stroke volume.", "optd": "During isothermal compression of air, the workdone in a compressor is maximum.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the aircraft propellers", "opta": "the propulsive matter is ejected from within the propelled body", "optb": "the propulsive matter is caused to flow around the propelled body", "optc": "its functioning does not depend upon the presence of air", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of rotary compressor used in gas turbines, is of", "opta": "centrifugal type", "optb": "axial flow type", "optc": "radial flow type", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The volume of air delivered by the compressor is called", "opta": "free air delivery", "optb": "compressor capacity", "optc": "swept volume", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a jet engine is higher at", "opta": "low speeds", "optb": "high speeds", "optc": "low altitudes", "optd": "high altitudes", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In axial flow compressor, exit flow angle deviation from the blade angle is a function of", "opta": "blade camber", "optb": "blade camber and incidence angle", "optc": "space-chord ratio", "optd": "blade camber and space-chord ratio", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rotary compressors are used for delivering", "opta": "small quantities of air at high pressures", "optb": "large quantities of air at high pressures", "optc": "small quantities of air at low pressures", "optd": "large quantities of air at low pressures", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Workdone by a two-stage reciprocating air compressor per cycle is equal to the workdone in LP. cylinder and H.P. cylinder.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rotary compressor is driven by an", "opta": "electric motor", "optb": "engine", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a centrifugal compressor, an increase in speed at a given pressure ratio causes", "opta": "increase in flow", "optb": "decrease in flow", "optc": "increase in efficiency", "optd": "increase in flow and decrease in efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A large clearance Volume in a reciprocating compressor results in", "opta": "reduced volume flow rate", "optb": "increased volume flow rate", "optc": "lower suction pressure", "optd": "lower delivery pressure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A closed cycle gas turbine gives __________ efficiency as compared to an open cycle gas turbine.", "opta": "same", "optb": "lower", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gas turbine as compared to steam turbine", "opta": "requires less space for installation", "optb": "has compressor and combustion chamber", "optc": "has less efficiency", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in gas turbines", "opta": "decreases net output but increases thermal efficiency", "optb": "increases net output but decreases thermal efficiency", "optc": "decreases net output and thermal efficiency both", "optd": "increases net output and thermal efficiency both", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the temperature of air leaving the intercooler, in a two stage compression with intercooler, is __________ the original atmospheric air temperature, then the intercooling is known as perfect or complete intercooling.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The actual volume of air delivered by a compressor, When reduced to the normal temperature and pressure conditions is called compressor capacity.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compression ratio in a gas turbine is", "opta": "4", "optb": "1", "optc": "9", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Intercooling in compressors results in saving of power in compressing given volume of air to a given pressure.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Only rocket engines can be propelled to space because", "opta": "they can generate very high thrust", "optb": "they have high propulsion efficiency", "optc": "these engines can work on several fuels", "optd": "they are not air-breathing engines", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum combustion pressure in gas turbine is __________ as compared to I.C. engine.", "opta": "more", "optb": "less", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An aftercooler is used to", "opta": "remove impurities from air", "optb": "reduce volume of air", "optc": "cause moisture and oil vapour to drop out", "optd": "cool the air", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High air-fuel ratio in gas turbines", "opta": "increases power output", "optb": "improves thermal efficiency", "optc": "reduces exhaust temperature", "optd": "do not damage turbine blades", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the volume of free air delivery per stroke to the swept volume of the piston, is known as", "opta": "compressor efficiency", "optb": "volumetric efficiency", "optc": "isothermal efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If p1, is the pressure of air entering the L.P. cylinder and p2 is the pressure of air leaving the L.P. cylinder (or intercooler pressure), then the ratio of cylinder diameters for a single acting, two stage reciprocating air compressor with complete intercooling is given by (where D1 = Dia. of L.P. cylinder, and D2 = Dia. of H.P. cylinder)", "opta": "D1/D2 = p1p2", "optb": "D1/D2 = p1/p2", "optc": "D1/D2 = p2/p1", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the indicated power to the shaft power or brake power of the motor or engine required to drive the compressor, is called", "opta": "compressor efficiency", "optb": "volumetric efficiency", "optc": "isothermal efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase in pressure in a roots blower is entirely due to back flow of air.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of rotary compressor used in aeroplanes, is of", "opta": "centrifugal type", "optb": "axial flow type", "optc": "radial flow type", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An axial compressor gives optimum performance at high speeds and large volume flows.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reciprocating air compressor, the compression work per kg of air", "opta": "increases as clearance volume increases", "optb": "decreases as clearance volume increases", "optc": "is independent of clearance volume", "optd": "increases as clearance volume decreases", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The degree of reaction in an axial flow compressor is defined as the ratio of static enthalpy rise in the", "opta": "rotor to static enthalpy rise in the stator", "optb": "stator to static enthalpy rise in the rotor", "optc": "rotor to static enthalpy rise in the stage", "optd": "stator to static enthalpy rise in the stage", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Specify the sequence correctly", "opta": "Grain growth, recrystallisation, stress relief", "optb": "Stress relief, grain growth, recrystallisation", "optc": "Stress relief, recrystallisation, grain growth", "optd": "Grain growth, stress relief, recrystallisation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermoplastic materials are those materials which", "opta": "are formed into shape under heat and pressure and results in a permanently hard product", "optb": "do not become hard with the application of heat and pressure and no chemical change occurs", "optc": "are flexible and can withstand considerable wear under suitable conditions", "optd": "are used as a friction lining for clutches and brakes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following material has maximum ductility?", "opta": "Mild steel", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Nickel", "optd": "Aluminium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An eutectoid steel consists of", "opta": "wholly pearlite", "optb": "wholly austenite", "optc": "pearlite and ferrite", "optd": "pearlite and cementite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shock resisting steels should have", "opta": "low wear resistance", "optb": "low hardness", "optc": "low tensile strength", "optd": "toughness", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron is a", "opta": "ductile material", "optb": "malleable material", "optc": "brittle material", "optd": "tough material", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness is the property of a material due to which it", "opta": "can be drawn into wires", "optb": "breaks with little permanent distortion", "optc": "can cut another metal", "optd": "can be rolled or hammered into thin sheets", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Malleable cast iron is produced", "opta": "by adding magnesium to molten cast iron", "optb": "by quick cooling of molten cast iron", "optc": "from white cast iron by annealing process", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smelting is the process of", "opta": "removing the impurities like clay, sand etc. from the iron ore by washing with water", "optb": "expelling moisture, carbon dioxide, sulphur and arsenic from the iron ore by heating in shallow kilns", "optc": "reducing the ore with carbon in the presence of a flux", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The percentage of carbon in cast iron varies from", "opta": "0.1 to 0.5", "optb": "0.5 to 1", "optc": "1 to 1.7", "optd": "1.7 to 4.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ability of a material to absorb energy in the plastic range is called", "opta": "resilience", "optb": "creep", "optc": "fatigue strength", "optd": "toughness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brass is an alloy of", "opta": "copper and zinc", "optb": "copper and tin", "optc": "copper, tin and zinc", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material is said to be allotropic, if it has", "opta": "fixed structure at all temperatures", "optb": "atoms distributed in random pattern", "optc": "different crystal structures at different temperatures", "optd": "any one of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Closed packed hexagonal space lattice is found in", "opta": "zinc, magnesium, cobalt, cadmium, antimony and bismuth", "optb": "gamma-iron, aluminium, copper, lead, silver and nickel", "optc": "alpha-iron, tungsten, chromium and molybdenum", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness and tensile strength in austenitic stainless steel can be increased by", "opta": "hardening and cold working", "optb": "normalising", "optc": "martempering", "optd": "full annealing", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quenching of steel from the upper critical point results in a fine grained structure.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An alloy steel which is work hardenable and which is used to make the blades of bulldozers, bucket wheel excavators and other earth moving equipment contain iron, carbon and", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "silicon", "optc": "manganese", "optd": "magnesium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has a fine gold colour and is used for imitation jewellery?", "opta": "Silicon bronze", "optb": "Aluminium bronze", "optc": "Gun metal", "optd": "Babbit metal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the steel is normalised, its", "opta": "yield point increases", "optb": "ductility decreases", "optc": "ultimate tensile strength increases", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "White cast iron has a high tensile strength and a low compressive strength.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "White cast iron has a low tensile strength and a high compressive strength.\nSource: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cast_iron#Table_of_comparative_qualities_of_cast_irons"}, {"question": "Dye penetrant method is generally used to locate", "opta": "core defects", "optb": "surface defects", "optc": "superficial defects", "optd": "temporary defects", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The charge is fed into the blast furnace through the", "opta": "stack", "optb": "throat", "optc": "bosh", "optd": "tuyers", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A small percentage of boron is added to steel in order to", "opta": "increase hardenability", "optb": "reduce machinability", "optc": "increase wear resistance", "optd": "increase endurance strength", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following process of steel making is in operation at Tata Iron and Steel Works, Jamshedpur?", "opta": "Bessemer process", "optb": "Open hearth process", "optc": "Duplex process", "optd": "Electric process", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit cells", "opta": "contain the smallest number of atoms which when taken together have all the properties of the crystals of the particular metal", "optb": "have the same orientation and their similar faces are parallel", "optc": "may be defined as the smallest parallelopiped which could be transposed in three coordinate directions to build up the space lattice", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tungsten when added to steel __________ the critical temperature.", "opta": "does not effect", "optb": "lowers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Silicon when added to copper improves", "opta": "machinability", "optb": "hardness", "optc": "hardness and strength", "optd": "strength and ductility", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The alloying element which increases residual magnetism and coercive magnetic force in steel for magnets is", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "vanadium", "optd": "cobalt", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron is manufactured in", "opta": "blast furnace", "optb": "cupola", "optc": "open hearth furnace", "optd": "bessemer converter", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lower critical point for all steels is", "opta": "600\u00b0C", "optb": "700\u00b0C", "optc": "723\u00b0C", "optd": "913\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Haematite iron ore contains iron about", "opta": "30%", "optb": "45%", "optc": "55%", "optd": "70%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The material in which the atoms are arranged regularly in some directions but not in others, is called", "opta": "amorphous material", "optb": "mesomorphous material", "optc": "crystalline material", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steel produced by bessemer or open hearth process is __________ to that produced by L-D process.", "opta": "superior", "optb": "inferior", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crystal structure of a material is, generally, examined by", "opta": "naked eye", "optb": "optical microscope", "optc": "metallurgical microscope", "optd": "X-ray techniques", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron-carbon alloys containing 1.7 to 4.3% carbon are known as", "opta": "eutectic cast irons", "optb": "hypo-eutectic cast irons", "optc": "hyper-eutectic cast irons", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coke in the charge of blast furnace", "opta": "controls the grade of pig iron", "optb": "acts as an iron-bearing mineral", "optc": "supplies heat to reduce ore and melt the iron", "optd": "forms a slag by combining with impurities", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nimonic contains __________ percentage of nickel as that of Inconel.", "opta": "same", "optb": "less", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat treatment process used for softening hardened steel is", "opta": "carburising", "optb": "normalising", "optc": "annealing", "optd": "tempering", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dieing down of a white flame during the operation of a bessemer converter indicates that the air is burning out silicon and manganese.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The electric process of steel making is especially adopted to", "opta": "alloy and carbon tool steel", "optb": "magnet steel", "optc": "high speed tool steel", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron ore is, usually, found in the form of", "opta": "oxides", "optb": "carbonates", "optc": "sulphides", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness of steel increases if it contains", "opta": "pearlite", "optb": "ferrite", "optc": "cementite", "optd": "martensite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In full annealing, the hypo-eutectoid steel is heated from 30\u00b0 C to 50\u00b0 C above the upper critical temperature and then cooled", "opta": "in still air", "optb": "slowly in the furnace", "optc": "suddenly in a suitable cooling medium", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ferrite and pearlite makes the steel soft and ductile.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lower critical temperature", "opta": "decreases as the carbon content in steel increases", "optb": "increases as the carbon content in steel increases", "optc": "is same for all steels", "optd": "depends upon the rate of heating", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nodular cast iron is produced by adding __________ to the molten cast iron.", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "chromium", "optc": "copper", "optd": "magnesium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Free carbon in iron makes the metal", "opta": "soft and gives a coarse grained crystalline structure", "optb": "soft and gives a fine grained crystalline structure", "optc": "hard and gives a coarse grained crystalline structure", "optd": "hard and gives a fine grained crystalline structure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cupola is used to manufacture", "opta": "pig iron", "optb": "cast iron", "optc": "wrought iron", "optd": "steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of space lattice found in gamma-iron is", "opta": "face centred cubic space lattice", "optb": "body centred cubic space lattice", "optc": "close packed hexagonal space lattice", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The property of a material due to which it breaks with little permanent distortion, is called", "opta": "brittleness", "optb": "ductility", "optc": "malleability", "optd": "plasticity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to principle of conservation of energy, the total momentum of a system of masses in any direction remains constant unless acted upon by an external force in that direction.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The friction experienced by a body, when in motion, is known as", "opta": "rolling friction", "optb": "dynamic friction", "optc": "limiting friction", "optd": "static friction", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two balls of equal mass and of perfectly elastic material are lying on the floor. One of the ball with velocity v is made to struck the second ball. Both the balls after impact will move with a velocity", "opta": "v", "optb": "v/2", "optc": "v/4", "optd": "v/8", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term 'force' may be defined as an agent which produces or tends to produce, destroys or tends to destroy motion.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of restitution for elastic bodies is one.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Coefficient of restitution for elastic bodies is 0 - 1.\nCoefficient of restitution for perfect elastic bodies is 1."}, {"question": "The velocity ratio in case of an inclined plane inclined at angle \u03b8 to the horizontal and weight being pulled up the inclined plane by vertical effort is", "opta": "sin \u03b8", "optb": "cos \u03b8", "optc": "tan \u03b8", "optd": "cosec \u03b8", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The range of projectile on a downward inclined plane is __________ the range on upward inclined plane for the same velocity of projection and angle of projection.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "more than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle of inclination of a vehicle when moving along a circular path __________ upon its mass.", "opta": "depends", "optb": "does not depend", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A body of weight W is required to move up on rough inclined plane whose angle of inclination with the horizontal is \u03b1. The effort applied parallel to the plane is given by(where \u03bc = tan\u03c6 = Coefficient of friction between the plane and the body.)", "opta": "P = W tan\u03b1", "optb": "P = W tan(\u03b1 + \u03c6)", "optc": "P = W (sin\u03b1 + \u03bccos\u03b1)", "optd": "P = W (cos\u03b1 + \u03bcsin\u03b1)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the resultant of two equal forces has the same magnitude as either of the forces, then the angle between the two forces is", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "60\u00b0", "optc": "90\u00b0", "optd": "120\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A smooth cylinder lying on its convex surface remains in __________ equilibrium.", "opta": "stable", "optb": "unstable", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coefficient of friction is the ratio of the limiting friction to the normal reaction between the two bodies.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moment of inertia of a circular section about an axis perpendicular to the section is", "opta": "\u03c0d3/16", "optb": "\u03c0d3/32", "optc": "\u03c0d4/32", "optd": "\u03c0d4/64", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time of flight (t) of a projectile on an upward inclined plane is(where u   =   Velocity of projection, \u03b1   =   Angle of projection, and \u03b2   =   Inclination of the plane with the horizontal.)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit of angular acceleration is", "opta": "N-m", "optb": "m/s", "optc": "m/s2", "optd": "rad/s2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moment of inertia of a triangular section of base (b) and height (h) about an axis passing through its C.G. and parallel to the base, is", "opta": "bh3/4", "optb": "bh3/8", "optc": "bh3/12", "optd": "bh3/36", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the masses of both the bodies, as shown in the below figure, are reduced to 50 percent, then tension in the string will be", "opta": "same", "optb": "half", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an equation of linear motion?(where, u and v = Initial and final velocity of the body, a = Acceleration of the body, and s = Displacement of the body in time t seconds.)", "opta": "v = u + a.t", "optb": "s = u.t + 1/2 a.t2", "optc": "v2 = u2+2a.s", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a number of forces are acting at a point, theirresultant will be inclined at an angle \u03b8 with the horizontal, such that", "opta": "tan \u03b8 = \u2211H/\u2211V", "optb": "tan \u03b8 = \u2211V/\u2211H", "optc": "tan \u03b8 = \u2211Vx\u2211H", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The above figure shows the two equal forces at right angles acting at a point. The value of force R acting along their bisector and in opposite direction is", "opta": "P/2", "optb": "2P", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force required to move the body up the plane will be minimum if it makes an angle with the inclined plane __________ the angle of friction.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the shown figure, if the angle of inclination of the plane is increased, then acceleration of the system will", "opta": "increase", "optb": "decrease", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total time taken by a projectile to reach maximum height and to return back to the ground, is known as time of flight.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The frequency of oscillation of a torsional pendulum is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The range of a projectile is maximum, when the angle of projection is", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "45\u00b0", "optc": "60\u00b0", "optd": "90\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mechanical advantage of a lifting machine is the ratio of", "opta": "distance moved by effort to the distance moved by load", "optb": "load lifted to the effort applied", "optc": "output to the input", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Static friction is always __________ dynamic friction.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A body will begin to move down an inclined plane if the angle of inclination of the plane is __________ the angle of friction.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a particle moves along a circular path with uniform velocity, there will be no tangential acceleration.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bodies which rebound after impact are called", "opta": "inelastic bodies", "optb": "elastic bodies", "optc": "neither elastic nor inelastic bodies", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum frictional force, which comes into play, when a body just begins to slide over the surface of the other body, is known as", "opta": "static friction", "optb": "dynamic friction", "optc": "limiting friction", "optd": "coefficient of friction", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre of gravity of an equilateral triangle with each side a, is __________ from any of the three sides.", "opta": "3a/2", "optb": "23a", "optc": "a/23", "optd": "32a", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance, between the point of projection and the point where the projectile strikes the ground, is known as range.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The algebraic sum of the resolved parts of a number of forces in a given direction is equal to the resolved part of their resultant in the same direction. This is known as", "opta": "principle of independence of forces", "optb": "principle of resolution of forces", "optc": "principle of transmissibility of forces", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The triangle law of forces states that if two forces acting simultaneously on a particle, be represented in magnitude and direction by the two sides of a triangle taken in order, then their resultant may be represented in magnitude and direction by the third side of a triangle, taken in opposite order.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle between two forces when the resultant is maximum and minimum respectively are", "opta": "0\u00b0 and 180\u00b0", "optb": "180\u00b0 and 0\u00b0", "optc": "90\u00b0 and 180\u00b0", "optd": "90\u00b0 and 0\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The path of the projectile is a parabola.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equivalent length of a simple pendulum which gives the same frequency as compound pendulum is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A redundant frame is also called __________ frame.", "opta": "perfect", "optb": "imperfect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass moment of inertia of a uni form thin rod of mass M and length (l) about its mid-point and perpendicular to its length is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A resultant force is a single force which produces the same effect as produced by all the given forces acting on a body.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a rigid body is suspended vertically, and it oscillates with a small amplitude under the action of the force of gravity, the body is known as", "opta": "simple pendulum", "optb": "compound pendulum", "optc": "torsional pendulum", "optd": "second's pendulum", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moment of inertia of a hollow circular section, as shown in the below figure about X-axis, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If two blocks of equal mass are attached to the two ends of a light string and one of the blocks is placed over a smooth horizontal plane while the other is hung freely after passing over a smooth pulley, then the two blocks will have some motion.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During elastic impact, the relative velocity of the two bodies after impact is __________ the relative velocity of the two bodies before impact.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "equal and opposite to", "optc": "less than", "optd": "greater than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work done is said to be zero, when", "opta": "some force acts on a body, but displacement is zero", "optb": "no force acts on a body but some displacement takes place", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force which acts along the radius of a circle and directed away from the centre of the circle is called centrifugal force.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One watt is equal to", "opta": "0.1 joule/s", "optb": "1 joule/s", "optc": "10 joules/s", "optd": "100 joules/s", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "two like parallel forces are acting at a distance of 24 mm apart and their resultant is 20 N. It the line of action of the resultant is 6 mm from any given force, the two forces are", "opta": "15 N and 5 N", "optb": "20 N and 5 N", "optc": "15 N and 15 N", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If two bodies having masses m1 and m2 (m1>m2) have equal kinetic energies, the momentum of body having mass m1 is __________ the momentum of body having mass m2.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wet bulb temperature during sensible heating of air", "opta": "remains constant", "optb": "increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The C.O.P. of an absorption type refrigerator is given by (where T1 = Temperature at which the working substance receives heat, T2 = Temperature of cooling water, and T3 = Evaporator temperature)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong?", "opta": "The heat transfer in liquid and gases takes place according to convection.", "optb": "The amount of heat flow through a body is dependent upon the material of the body.", "optc": "The thermal conductivity of solid metals increases with rise in temperature,", "optd": "Logarithmic mean temperature difference is not equal to the arithmetic mean temperature difference.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In free convection heat transfer transition from laminar to turbulent flow is governed by the critical value of the", "opta": "Reynold's number", "optb": "Grashoff's number", "optc": "Reynold's number, Grashoff's number", "optd": "Prandtl number, Grashoff's number", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a refrigerating machine, heat rejected is __________ heat absorbed.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The humidity ratio or specific humidity is the mass of water vapour present in", "opta": "1 m3 of wet air", "optb": "1 m3 of dry air", "optc": "1 kg of wet air", "optd": "1 kg of dry air", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The formation of frost on cooling coils in a refrigerator", "opta": "increases heat transfer", "optb": "improves C.O.P. of the system", "optc": "increases power consumption", "optd": "reduces power consumption", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The by-pass factor for a cooling coil", "opta": "increases with increase in velocity of air passing through it", "optb": "decreases with increase in velocity of air passing through it", "optc": "remains unchanged with increase in velocity of air passing through it", "optd": "may increase or decrease with increase in velocity of air passing through it depending upon the condition of air entering", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference between dry bulb temperature and wet bulb temperature, is called", "opta": "dry bulb depression", "optb": "wet bulb depression", "optc": "dew point depression", "optd": "degree of saturation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Defrosting of a refrigerator may be done by stopping the compressor for a short period.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Dalton's law of partial pressures, (where pb = Barometric pressure, pa = Partial pressure of dry air, and pv = Partial pressure of water vapour)", "opta": "Pb = pa - pv", "optb": "Pb = pa + pv", "optc": "Pb = pa x pv", "optd": "Pb = pa/pv", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat transfer by conduction through a thick sphere is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The relative humidity is defined as", "opta": "the mass of water vapour present in 1 m3 of dry air", "optb": "the mass of water vapour present in 1 kg of dry air", "optc": "the ratio of the actual mass of water vapour in a unit mass of dry air to the mass of water vapour in the same mass of dry air when it is saturated at the same temperature and pressure.", "optd": "the ratio of actual mass of water vapour in a given volume of moist air to the mass of water vapour in the same volume of saturated air at the same temperature and pressure", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fourier's law of heat conduction is (where Q = Amount of heat flow through the body in unit time, A = Surface area of heat flow, taken at right angles to the direction of heat flow, dT = Temperature difference on the two faces of the body, dx = Thickness of the body, through which the heat flows, taken along the direction of heat flow, and k = Thermal conductivity of the body)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat transfer by conduction through a thick sphere is same as through a thick cylinder.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In aqua-ammonia and Lithium-bromide water absorption refrigeration systems, the refrigerants are respectively", "opta": "water and water", "optb": "water and lithium bromide", "optc": "ammonia and lithium bromide", "optd": "ammonia and water", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As relative humidity decreases, the dew point temperature will be __________ wet bulb temperature.", "opta": "same as", "optb": "lower than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The process of heat transfer from a hot body to a cold body, in a straight line, without affecting the intervening medium, is called radiation.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reynolds number (RN) is given by (where h = Film coefficient, l = Linear dimension, V = Velocity of fluid, k = Thermal conductivity, t = Temperature, \u03c1 = Density of fluid, cp = Specific heat at constant pressure, and \u03bc = Coefficient of absolute viscosity)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The optimum effective temperature for human comfort is", "opta": "higher in winter than in summer", "optb": "lower in winter than in summer", "optc": "same in winter and summer", "optd": "not dependent on season", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The wet bulb temperature lines, on the psychrometric chart, are curved lines.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sensible heat factor during cooling and dehumidification process is given by (where h1 = Enthalpy of air entering the cooling coil, h2 = Enthalpy of air leaving the cooling coil, and hA = Enthalpy of air at the end of dehumidification process)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal diffusivity is a", "opta": "function of temperature", "optb": "physical property of a substance", "optc": "dimensionless parameter", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The condition of refrigerant after leaving the compressor and before entering the condenser is superheated vapour.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total radiation from a black body per second per unit area is __________ fourth power of the absolute temperature. This statement is known as Stefan-Boltzmann law.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "directly proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following represents a heat pump?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a psychrometric process, the sensible heat added is 30 kJ/s and the latent heat added is 20 kJ/s. The sensible heat factor for the process will be", "opta": "0.3", "optb": "0.6", "optc": "0.67", "optd": "1.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of radiation mainly depends upon the", "opta": "nature of the body", "optb": "temperature of the body", "optc": "type of surface of the body", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For ammonia refrigerating systems, the tubes of a shell and tube condenser are made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "steel", "optd": "brass", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The highest thermal diffusivity is of", "opta": "iron", "optb": "lead", "optc": "concrete", "optd": "wood", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While designing the refrigeration system of an aircraft, the prime consideration is that the", "opta": "system has high C.O.P.", "optb": "power per TR is low", "optc": "mass of refrigerant circulated in the system is low", "optd": "mass of the refrigeration equipment is low", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat transfer takes place according to", "opta": "Zeroth law of thermodynamics", "optb": "First law of thermodynamics", "optc": "Second law of thermodynamics", "optd": "Kirchhoff's law", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An electrolux refrigerator is called a __________ absorption system.", "opta": "single fluid", "optb": "two fluids", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat transfer by radiation __________ a medium.", "opta": "requires", "optb": "does not require", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal conductivity of water __________ with rise in temperature.", "opta": "remains same", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "increases", "optd": "may increase or decrease depending upon temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During adiabatic saturation process on unsaturated air __________ remains constant.", "opta": "relative humidity", "optb": "dew point temperature", "optc": "dry bulb temperature", "optd": "wet bulb temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness of thermal and hydrodynamic boundary layer is equal if Prandtl number is", "opta": "equal to one", "optb": "greater than one", "optc": "less than one", "optd": "equal to Nusselt number", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A perfect black body is one which", "opta": "is black in colour", "optb": "absorbs heat radiations of all wave lengths falling on it", "optc": "reflects all the heat radiations", "optd": "transmits the heat radiations", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Degree of saturation or percentage humidity is", "opta": "the mass of water vapour present in 1 m3 of dry air", "optb": "the mass of water vapour present in 1 kg of dry air", "optc": "the ratio of the actual mass of water vapour in a unit mass of dry air to the mass of water vapour in the same mass of dry air when it is saturated at the same temperature and pressure.", "optd": "the ratio of actual mass of water vapour in a given volume of moist air to the mass of water vapour in the same volume of saturated air at the same temperature and pressure", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of performance of Heat Pump is always __________ one.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During a refrigeration cycle, heat is rejected by the refrigerant in a", "opta": "compressor", "optb": "condenser", "optc": "evaporator", "optd": "expansion valve", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A refrigeration system", "opta": "removes heat from a low temperature body and delivers it to a high temperature body", "optb": "removes heat from a high temperature body and delivers it to a low temperature body", "optc": "rejects energy to a low temperature body", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The subcooling in a refrigeration cycle", "opta": "does not alter C.O.P.", "optb": "increases C.O.P.", "optc": "decreases C.O.P.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nusselt number (NN) is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During sensible cooling of air __________ decreases.", "opta": "wet bulb temperature", "optb": "relative humidity", "optc": "dry bulb temperature", "optd": "specific humidity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical radius is the insulation radius at which the resistance to heat flow is", "opta": "maximum", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "zero", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of solids, the heat transfer takes place according to radiation.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A water cooled condenser operates at a __________ condensing temperature than an air-cooled condenser.", "opta": "higher", "optb": "lower", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The relative humidity decreases as air gets wet.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature of ammonia after compression in a vapour compression system is", "opta": "20 to 50\u00b0 C", "optb": "50 to 70\u00b0 C", "optc": "70 to 110\u00b0 C", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One litre of water occupies a volume of", "opta": "100 cm3", "optb": "250 cm3", "optc": "500 cm3", "optd": "1000 cm3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of bulk modulus of a fluid is required to determine", "opta": "Reynold's number", "optb": "Froude's number", "optc": "Mach number", "optd": "Euler's number", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a depressed nappe", "opta": "the pressure below the nappe is atmospheric", "optb": "the pressure below the nappe is negative", "optc": "the pressure above the nappe is atmospheric", "optd": "the pressure above the nappe is negative", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In one dimensional flow, the flow", "opta": "is steady and uniform", "optb": "takes place in straight line", "optc": "takes place in curve", "optd": "takes place in one direction", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The kinematic viscosity is the", "opta": "ratio of absolute viscosity to the density of the liquid", "optb": "ratio of density of the liquid to the absolute viscosity", "optc": "product of absolute viscosity and density of the liquid", "optd": "product of absolute viscosity and mass of the liquid", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter of the nozzle (d) for maximum transmission of power is given by (where D = Diameter of pipe, f = Darcy 's coefficient of friction for pipe, and l = Length of pipe )", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge over a right angled notch is (where H = Height of liquid above the apex of notch)", "opta": "Cd 2g x H", "optb": "Cd 2g x H3/2", "optc": "Cd 2g x H2", "optd": "Cd 2g x H5/2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A weir is said to be broad crested weir, if the width of the crest of the weir is __________ half the height of water above the weir crest.", "opta": "equal to.", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A vertical wall is subjected to a pressure due to one kind of liquid, on one of its sides. The total pressure on the wall per unit length is (where w = Specific weight of liquid, and H = Height of liquid)", "opta": "wH", "optb": "wH/2", "optc": "wH2/2", "optd": "wH2/3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An error of 1% in measuring head over the apex of the notch (H) will produce an error of __________ in discharge over a triangular notch.", "opta": "1%", "optb": "1.5%", "optc": "2%", "optd": "2.5%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length AB of a pipe ABC in which the liquid is flowing has diameter (d1) and is suddenly enlarged to diameter (d2) at B which is constant for the length BC. The loss of head due to sudden enlargement is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coefficient of contraction is the ratio of", "opta": "actual velocity of jet at vena contracta to the theoretical velocity", "optb": "loss of head in the orifice to the head of water available at the exit of the orifice", "optc": "actual discharge through an orifice to the theoretical discharge", "optd": "area of jet at vena contracta to the area of orifice", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a free nappe,", "opta": "the pressure below the nappe is atmospheric", "optb": "the pressure below the nappe is negative", "optc": "the pressure above the nappe is atmospheric", "optd": "the pressure above the nappe is negative", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Reynold's number of a ship is __________ to its velocity and length.", "opta": "directly proportional", "optb": "inversely proportional", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a tube of smaller diameter is dipped in water, the water rises in the tube due to viscosity of water.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to equation of continuity,", "opta": "w1a1 = w2a2", "optb": "w1v1 = w2v2", "optc": "a1v1 = a2v2", "optd": "a1/v1 = a2/v2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coefficient of resistance is the ratio of", "opta": "actual velocity of jet at vena contracta to the theoretical velocity", "optb": "area of jet at vena contracta to the area of orifice", "optc": "loss of head in the orifice to the head of water available at the exit of the orifice", "optd": "actual discharge through an orifice to the dieoretical discharge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Euler's equation in the differential form for the motion of liquids is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "\u03c1.dp + g.dz + v.dv = 0", "optd": "\u03c1.dp - g.dz + v.dv = 0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to measure the flow with a venturimeter, it is installed in", "opta": "horizontal line", "optb": "inclined line with flow upwards", "optc": "inclined line with flow downwards", "optd": "any direction and in any location", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge through a large rectangular orifice is given by (where H1 = Height of the liquid above the top of the orifice, H2 = Height of the liquid above the bottom of the orifice, b = Breadth of the orifice, and Cd = Coefficient of discharge)", "opta": "Q =  Cd x b2g(H2 - H1)", "optb": "Q =  Cd x b2g(H21/2 - H11/2)", "optc": "Q =  Cd x b2g(H23/2 - H13/2)", "optd": "Q =  Cd x b2g(H22 - H12)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge over a rectangular notch is (where b = Width of notch, and H = Height of liquid, above the sill of the notch)", "opta": "Cd x b2gH", "optb": "Cd x b2g x H", "optc": "Cd x b2g x H3/2", "optd": "Cd x b2g x H2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge through a siphon spillway is", "opta": "Cd x a2gH", "optb": "Cd x a2g x H3/2", "optc": "Cd x a2g x H2", "optd": "Cd x a2g x H5/2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum discharge over a broad crested weir is", "opta": "0.384 Cd x L x H1/2", "optb": "0.384 Cd x L x H3/2", "optc": "1.71 Cd x L x H1/2", "optd": "1.71 Cd x L x H3/2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a venturimeter, the velocity of liquid at throat is __________ than at inlet.", "opta": "higher", "optb": "lower", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The loss of head due to friction in a pipe of uniform diameter in which a viscous flow is taking place, is (where RN = Reynold number)", "opta": "1/RN", "optb": "4/RN", "optc": "16/RN", "optd": "64/RN", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an example of laminar flow?", "opta": "Under ground flow", "optb": "Flow past tiny bodies", "optc": "Flow of oil in measuring instruments", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure less than atmospheric pressure is known as", "opta": "suction pressure", "optb": "vacuum pressure", "optc": "negative gauge pressure", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total energy line lies over the hydraulic gradient line by an amount equal to the", "opta": "pressure head", "optb": "velocity head", "optc": "pressure head + velocity head", "optd": "pressure head - velocity head", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A structure whose width is __________ the width of the channel, is called a flumed structure.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "more than", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum efficiency of transmission through a pipe is", "opta": "50%", "optb": "56.7%", "optc": "66.67%", "optd": "76.66%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of viscosity may be determined by", "opta": "capillary tube method", "optb": "orifice type viscometer", "optc": "rotating cylinder method", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stability of a dam is checked for", "opta": "tension at the base", "optb": "overturning of the wall or dam", "optc": "sliding of the wall or dam", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal fluid is frictionless and incompressible.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A manometer is used to measure", "opta": "low pressure", "optb": "moderate pressure", "optc": "high pressure", "optd": "atomospheric pressure", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre of gravity of the volume of the liquid displaced is called", "opta": "centre of pressure", "optb": "centre of buoyancy", "optc": "metacentre", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coefficient of discharge for an external mouthpiece is", "opta": "0.375", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "0.707", "optd": "0.855", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A tank of uniform cross-sectional area (A) containing liquid upto height (H1) has an orifice of cross-sectional area (a) at its bottom. The time required to empty the tank completely will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A siphon is used to connect two reservoirs at different levels intervened by a high ridge.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A flow in which the volume of a fluid and its density does not change during the flow is called __________ flow.", "opta": "incompressible", "optb": "compressible", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The loss of head due to an obstruction in a pipe is twice the loss of head at its entrance.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The body will sink down if the force of buoyancy is __________ the weight of the liquid displaced.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a body floating in a liquid returns back to its original position, when given a small angular displacement, the body is said to be in", "opta": "neutral equilibrium", "optb": "stable equilibrium", "optc": "unstable equilibrium", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure measured with the help of a piezometer tube is in", "opta": "N/mm2", "optb": "N/m2", "optc": "head of liquid", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The power transmitted through a pipe is (where w = Specific weight in N/m3, and Q = Discharge in m3/s)", "opta": "w x Q x H", "optb": "w x Q x hf", "optc": "w x Q (H - hf)", "optd": "w x Q (H + hf)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an external mouthpiece, the absolute pressure head at vena contracta is __________ the atmospheric pressure head by an amount equal to 0.89 times the height of the liquid, above the vena contracta.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "more than", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight per unit volume of a liquid at a standard temperature and pressure is called", "opta": "specific weight", "optb": "mass density", "optc": "specific gravity", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre of buoyancy is the centre of area of the immersed body.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The metacentric heights of two floating bodies A and B are 1 m and 1.5 m respectively. Select the correct statement.", "opta": "The bodies A and B have equal stability", "optb": "The body A is more stable than body B", "optc": "The body B is more stable than body A", "optd": "The bodies A and B are unstable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In open channels, the specific energy is the", "opta": "total energy per unit discharge", "optb": "total energy measured with respect to the datum passing through the bottom of the channel", "optc": "total energy measured above the horizontal datum", "optd": "kinetic energy plotted above the free surface of water", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Bernoulli's equation is based on the assumption that", "opta": "there is no loss of energy of the liquid flowing", "optb": "the velocity of flow is uniform across any cross-section of the pipe", "optc": "no force except gravity acts on the fluid", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power required to drive a centrifugal pump is directly proportional to __________ of its impeller.", "opta": "diameter", "optb": "square of diameter", "optc": "cube of diameter", "optd": "fourth power of diameter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mechanical efficiency of an impulse turbine is", "opta": "ratio of the actual power produced by the turbine to the energy actually supplied by the turbine", "optb": "ratio of the actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel", "optc": "ratio of the Work done on the wheel to the energy of the jet", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The overshot water wheels are those in which the wheel runs entirely by the __________ of water.", "opta": "weight", "optb": "impulse", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a Kaplan turbine runner, the number of blades are generally between", "opta": "2 to 4", "optb": "4 to 8", "optc": "8 to l6", "optd": "16 to 24", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If Hg is the gross or total head and hf is the head lost due to friction, then net or effective head (H) is given by", "opta": "H = Hg/hf", "optb": "H = Hg x hf", "optc": "H = Hg + hf", "optd": "H = Hg - hf", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge of a centrifugal pump is", "opta": "directly proportional to diameter of its impeller", "optb": "inversely proportional to diameter of its impeller", "optc": "directly proportional to (diameter)2 of its impeller", "optd": "inversely proportional to (diameter)2 of its impeller", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Pelton wheel develops 1750 kW under a head of 100 metres while running at 200 r.p.m. and discharging 2500 litres of water per second. The unit power of the wheel is", "opta": "0.25 kW", "optb": "0.75 kW", "optc": "1.75 kW", "optd": "3.75 kW", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The static head of a centrifugal pump is equal to the __________ of suction head and delivery head.", "opta": "product", "optb": "difference", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel is known as __________ efficiency.", "opta": "hydraulic", "optb": "mechanical", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Geometric similarity is said to exist between the model and the prototype, if both of them", "opta": "have identical velocities", "optb": "are equal in size and shape", "optc": "are identical in shape, but differ only in size", "optd": "have identical forces", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed of a turbine runner is", "opta": "directly proportional to H1/2", "optb": "inversely proportional to H1/2", "optc": "directly proportional to H3/2", "optd": "inversely proportional to H3/2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A ship with jet propulsion draws water through inlet orifices at right angles to the direction of its motion. The propelling force of the jet is (where a = Area of the jet, Vr = Relative velocity of the jet and ship = V + v, v = Velocity of the ship, and V = Velocity of the jet issuing from the ship)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge of a centrifugal pump is (where N = Speed of the pump impeller)", "opta": "directly proportional to N", "optb": "inversely proportional to N", "optc": "directly proportional to N2", "optd": "inversely proportional to N2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, the draft tube is used", "opta": "to run the turbine full", "optb": "to prevent air to enter the turbine", "optc": "to increase the head of water by an amount equal to the height of the runner outlet above the tail race", "optd": "to transport water to downstream", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The power produced by the reaction turbine is __________ to the head of water.", "opta": "directly proportional", "optb": "inversely proportional", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Slip of a reciprocating pump is defined as the", "opta": "ratio of actual discharge to the theoretical discharge", "optb": "sum of actual discharge and the theoretical discharge", "optc": "difference of theoretical discharge and the actual discharge", "optd": "product of theoretical discharge and the actual discharge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a centrifugal pump will be maximum when the blades are bent backward.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Multi-stage centrifugal pumps are used to", "opta": "give high discharge", "optb": "produce high heads", "optc": "pump viscous fluids", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific speed of a centrifugal pump, delivering 750 litres of water per second against a head of 15 metres at 725 r.p.m., is", "opta": "24.8 r.p.m.", "optb": "48.2 r.p.m", "optc": "82.4 r.p.m.", "optd": "248 r.p.m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Theoretical power required (in watts) to drive a reciprocating pump is (where w = Specific weight of liquid to be pumped in N/m3, Q = Discharge of the pump in m3/s, Hs = Suction head in metres, and Hd = Delivery head in metres)", "opta": "wQHs", "optb": "wQHd", "optc": "wQ(Hs - Hd)", "optd": "wQ(Hs + Hd)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following pump is preferred for flood control and irrigation applications?", "opta": "Centrifugal pump", "optb": "Axial flow pump", "optc": "Mixed flow pump", "optd": "Reciprocating pump", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a Pelton wheel working under constant head __________ with the increase in power.", "opta": "remains same", "optb": "increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of a centrifugal pump working under constant head __________ with the speed.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit discharge through the turbine is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Delivery head of water of a centrifugal pump is inversely proportional to diameter of its impeller.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of a double acting reciprocating pump is (where L = Length of stroke, A = Cross-sectional area of piston, and N = Speed of crank in r.p.m.)", "opta": "L.A.N", "optb": "2 L.A.N", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following turbine is preferred for 0 to 25 m head of water?", "opta": "Pelton wheel", "optb": "Kaplan turbine", "optc": "Francis turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed ratio of a Francis turbine is defined as the ratio of the theoretical jet velocity to the peripheral speed at inlet.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The overall efficiency of a reaction turbine is the ratio of", "opta": "power produced by the turbine to the energy actually supplied by the turbine", "optb": "actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel", "optc": "workdone on the wheel to the energy (or head of water) actually supplied to the turbine", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work done by a turbine __________ upon the weight of water flowing per second.", "opta": "depends", "optb": "does not depend", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum number of jets, generally, employed in an impulse turbine without jet interference are", "opta": "two", "optb": "four", "optc": "six", "optd": "eight", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reciprocating pump, air vessels are fitted to the suction pipe and delivery pipe close to the cylinder of the pump.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge (Q) of a centrifugal pump is given by (where D = Diameter of impeller at inlet, b = Width of impeller at inlet, and Vf = Velocity of flow at inlet)", "opta": "Q = \u03c0.D.Vf", "optb": "Q = \u03c0.b.Vf", "optc": "Q = \u03c0.D.b.Vf", "optd": "Q = D.b.Vf", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A centrifugal pump will start delivering liquid only when the pressure rise in the impeller is equal to the", "opta": "kinetic head", "optb": "velocity head", "optc": "manometric head", "optd": "static head", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the speed of the pump increases, its net positive suction head (NPSH) requirement decreases.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Francis turbine is used when the available head of water is", "opta": "0 to 25 m", "optb": "25 m to 250 m", "optc": "above 250 m", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific speed from 160 to 500 r.p.m. of a centrifugal pump indicates that the pump is", "opta": "slow speed with radial flow at outlet", "optb": "medium speed with radial flow at outlet", "optc": "high speed with radial flow at outlet", "optd": "high speed with axial flow at outlet", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic coupling belongs to the category of", "opta": "power absorbing machines", "optb": "power developing machines", "optc": "energy transfer machines", "optd": "energy generating machines", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The principle of jet propulsion is used in driving the ships and aeroplanes.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the casing of a centrifugal pump, the kinetic energy of the water is converted into pressure energy before the water leaves the casing.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed of an imaginary turbine, identical with the given turbine, which will develop a unit power under a unit head, is known as", "opta": "normal speed", "optb": "unit speed", "optc": "specific speed", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For centrifugal pump impeller, the maximum value of the vane exit angle is", "opta": "10\u00b0 to 15\u00b0", "optb": "15\u00b0 to 20\u00b0", "optc": "20\u00b0 to 25\u00b0", "optd": "25\u00b0 to 30\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, the pressure head of water, while flowing over the vanes, is converted into kinetic head before leaving the wheel.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Manometric head, in case of a centrifugal pump, is equal to", "opta": "Suction lift + Loss of head in suction pipe due to friction + Delivery lift + Loss of head in delivery pipe due to friction + Velocity head in the delivery pipe", "optb": "Workdone per kN of water - Losses within the impeller", "optc": "Energy per kN at outlet of impeller - Energy per kN at inlet of impeller", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force exerted by a jet of water (in a direction normal to flow) impinging on a fixed plate inclined at an angle \u03b8 with the jet is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an impulse turbine, the jet of water impinges on the bucket with a low velocity and after flowing over the vanes, leaves with a high velocity.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a hydraulic accumulator is generally specified as the maximum amount of energy stored.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum efficiency of jet propulsion of a ship with inlet orifices at right angles to the direction of motion of ship, is", "opta": "40%", "optb": "50%", "optc": "60%", "optd": "80%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The breast water wheels are those in which the wheel runs partly by the weight of water and partly by the impulse of water.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of quantity of liquid discharged per second from the pump to the quantity of liquid passing per second through the impeller is known as", "opta": "manometric efficiency", "optb": "mechanical efficiency", "optc": "overall efficiency", "optd": "volumetric efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reference fuels for knock rating of spark ignition engines would include", "opta": "iso-octane and alpha-methyl naphthalene", "optb": "normal octane and aniline", "optc": "iso-octane and normal hexane", "optd": "normal heptane and iso-octane", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diesel engines are also known as __________ engines.", "opta": "compression ignition", "optb": "spark ignition", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four stroke cycle, the minimum temperature inside the engine cylinder occurs at the", "opta": "beginning of suction stroke", "optb": "end of suction stroke", "optc": "beginning of exhaust stroke", "optd": "end of exhaust stroke", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In hit and miss governing, the fuel supply is cut-off completely during one or more number of cycles.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of a standard Otto cycle for a compression ratio of 5.5 will be", "opta": "25%", "optb": "50%", "optc": "70%", "optd": "100%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the volume of charge admitted at N.T.P. to the swept volume of the piston is called", "opta": "mechanical efficiency", "optb": "overall efficiency", "optc": "volumetric efficiency", "optd": "relative efficiency", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The exhaust valve in a four stroke cycle petrol engine", "opta": "opens at 50\u00b0 before bottom dead centre and closes at 15\u00b0 after top dead centre", "optb": "opens at bottom dead centre and closes at top dead centre", "optc": "opens at 50\u00b0 after bottom dead centre and closes at 15\u00b0 before top dead centre", "optd": "may open and close anywhere", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nuclear reactors are used", "opta": "to produce heat for thermoelectric power", "optb": "to produce fissionable material", "optc": "to propel ships, submarines, aircrafts", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A moderator generally used in nuclear power plants is", "opta": "graphite", "optb": "heavy water", "optc": "concrete", "optd": "graphite and concrete", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The predominent isotope of the naturally occuring element is", "opta": "U235", "optb": "U238", "optc": "Pu233", "optd": "Pu239", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The brake power of a diesel engine, keeping other parameters constant, can be increased by", "opta": "decreasing the density of intake air", "optb": "increasing the temperature of intake air", "optc": "increasing the pressure of intake air", "optd": "decreasing the pressure of intake air", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In diesel engines, the fuel is injected in the form of very fine spray, into the engine cylinder, which gets ignited due to high temperature of the compressed air.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pre-ignition is caused by the spontantaneous combustion of the mixture before the end of the compression stroke, and is due to", "opta": "cylinder walls being too hot", "optb": "overheated spark plug points", "optc": "red hot carbon deposits on cylinder walls", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expansion of fuel in a four stroke cycle diesel engine", "opta": "starts at 15\u00b0 before top dead centre and ends at 30\u00b0 after top dead centre", "optb": "starts at top dead centre and ends at 30\u00b0 after top dead centre", "optc": "starts at 15\u00b0 after top dead centre and ends at 30\u00b0 before bottom dead centre", "optd": "may start and end anywhere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The object of supercharging the engine is", "opta": "to reduce mass ofthe engine per brake power", "optb": "to reduce space occupied by the engine", "optc": "to increase the power output of an engine when greater power is required", "optd": "all ofthe above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In open combustion chamber in diesel engines, the shape and layout of the piston crown, the inlet port and the valve produce the turbulent effect of fuel mixture.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four stroke cycle petrol engine, the charge is ignited at", "opta": "30\u00b0 before top dead centre", "optb": "30\u00b0 after top dead centre", "optc": "30\u00b0 before bottom dead centre", "optd": "30\u00b0 after bottom dead centre", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A moderator, in nuclear power plants, is a medium introduced into the fuel mass in order to", "opta": "slow down the speed of fast moving neutrons", "optb": "control the reaction", "optc": "reduce the temperature", "optd": "extract heat from nuclear reaction", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Where reactor operation is designed with fast neutrons such as in reactors using highly enriched fuel, the moderator used is", "opta": "heavy water", "optb": "graphite", "optc": "carbon dioxide", "optd": "no moderator is needed", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a diesel engine, the duration between the time of injection and ignition, is known as", "opta": "pre-ignition period", "optb": "delay period", "optc": "period of ignition", "optd": "burning period", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The detonating tendency in petrol engines increases with increase of compression ratio.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Each fission of U235 produces on the average __________ fast neutrons as a product of reaction.", "opta": "2.46", "optb": "24.6", "optc": "246", "optd": "2460", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reactors for propulsion applications are designed for", "opta": "any form of uranium", "optb": "natura uranium", "optc": "enriched uranium", "optd": "plutonium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The primary fuel used in nuclear power plants is", "opta": "U235", "optb": "U238", "optc": "Pu239", "optd": "Pu233", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In petrol engine, using a fixed octane rating fuel and fixed compression ratio, supercharging will __________ the knocking tendency.", "opta": "not effect", "optb": "decrease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ordinary water is sometimes used as moderator when enriched uranium is used as a fuel in nuclear power plants.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compensating jet in a carburettor supplies almost constant amount of petrol at all speeds because the", "opta": "jet area is automatically varied depending on the suction", "optb": "the flow from the main jet is diverted to the compensating jet with increase in speed", "optc": "the diameter of the jet is constant and the discharge coefficient is invariant", "optd": "flow is produced due to the static head in the float chamber", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effective inhibitor of pre-ignition is", "opta": "alcohol", "optb": "water", "optc": "lead", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of testing an internal combustion engine is", "opta": "to determine the information, which can not be obtained by calculations", "optb": "to conform the data used in design, the validity of which may be doubtful", "optc": "to satisfy the customer regarding the performance of the engine", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of diesel engines is about", "opta": "15%", "optb": "30%", "optc": "50%", "optd": "70%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A diesel engine has", "opta": "one valve", "optb": "two valves", "optc": "three valves", "optd": "four valves", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The self ignition temperature of petrol is __________ as compared to diesel oil.", "opta": "same", "optb": "lower", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure inside the cylinder is __________ the atmospheric pressure during the exhaust stroke.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "below", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase of cooling water temperature in petrol engine will __________ the knocking tendency.", "opta": "not effect", "optb": "decrease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A carburettor is used to supply", "opta": "petrol, air and lubricating oil", "optb": "air and diesel", "optc": "petrol and lubricating oil", "optd": "petrol and air", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "U233 is produced", "opta": "artificially", "optb": "as basic raw material", "optc": "when thorium is irradiated by neutrons", "optd": "by fission of U238", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure at the end of compression, in diesel engines, is approximately", "opta": "10 bar", "optb": "20 bar", "optc": "25 bar", "optd": "35 bar", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The detonation is also called knocking or pinking.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pre-ignition occurs before the spark is produced whereas detonation develops after the introduction of spark.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy released during the fission of one atom of Uranium - 235 in million electron volts is about", "opta": "100", "optb": "200", "optc": "300", "optd": "400", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Morse test can be conducted for", "opta": "petrol engines", "optb": "diesel engines", "optc": "multi-cylinder engines", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The basic requirement of a good combustion chamber is", "opta": "minimum turbulence", "optb": "low compression ratio", "optc": "high thermal efficiency and power output", "optd": "low volumetric efficiency", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four stroke cycle petrol engine, the charge is compressed when both the valves (i.e. inlet valve and exit valve) are closed,", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of diesel engines on weak mixtures is", "opta": "unaffected", "optb": "lower", "optc": "higher", "optd": "dependent on other factors", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The injection pressure in a diesel engine is about", "opta": "10 bar", "optb": "100 bar", "optc": "150 bar", "optd": "500 bar", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High speed compression engines operate on", "opta": "Otto cycle", "optb": "Diesel cycle", "optc": "Dual-combustion cycle", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four stroke cycle petrol engine, the inlet valve", "opta": "opens at top dead centre and closes at bottom dead centre", "optb": "opens at 20\u00b0 before top dead centre and closes at 40\u00b0 after bottom dead centre", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The nuclear power station at Tarapur has the reactor of the __________ type.", "opta": "pressurized water", "optb": "boiling water", "optc": "gas cooled", "optd": "liquid metal cooled", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In nuclear power plants, due to reflector, less fuel is needed to generate sufficient neutrons to sustain a chain reaction.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The secondary fuel used in nuclear power plants is", "opta": "U233 and Pu239", "optb": "U235 and Th232", "optc": "U235 and Pu238", "optd": "U233 and Pu238", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The aim of value engineering is to", "opta": "find the depreciation value of a machine", "optb": "determine the selling price of a product", "optc": "minimise the cost without change in quality of the product", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In time study, the rating factor is applied to determine", "opta": "standard time of a job", "optb": "merit rating of the worker", "optc": "fixation of incentive rate", "optd": "normal time of a worker", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gantt chart is used for", "opta": "inventory control", "optb": "material handling", "optc": "production schedule", "optd": "machine repair schedules", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main object of scientific layout is", "opta": "to produce better quality of product", "optb": "to utilise maximum floor area", "optc": "to minimise production delays", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The probabilistic time is given by (where to = Optimistic time, tp = Pessimistic time, and tn = Most likely time)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In value engineering, the term value refers to", "opta": "manufacturing cost of the product", "optb": "selling price of the product", "optc": "total cost of the product", "optd": "utility of the product", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In inventory control theory, the economic order quantity is", "opta": "average level of inventory", "optb": "optimum lot size", "optc": "capacity of a warehouse", "optd": "lot size corresponding to break-even analysis", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Production cost refers to prime cost plus", "opta": "factory overheads", "optb": "factory and administration overheads", "optc": "factory, administration and sales overheads", "optd": "factory, administration, sales overheads and profit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A systematic job improvement sequence will consist of", "opta": "motion study", "optb": "time study", "optc": "job enrichment", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work sampling is applied for", "opta": "estimation of the percentage utilisation of machine tools", "optb": "estimating the percentage of the time consumed by various job activities", "optc": "finding out time standards, specially where the job is not repetitive and where time study by stop watch method is not possible", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Military type of organisation is known as", "opta": "line organisation", "optb": "functional organisation", "optc": "line and staff organisation", "optd": "line, staff and functional organisation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When slack of an activity is negative", "opta": "it represents a situation where extra resources are available and the completion of project is not delayed", "optb": "it represents that a programme falls behind schedule and additional resources are required to complete the project in time", "optc": "the activity is critical and any delay in its performance will delay the completion of whole project", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The procedure of modifying work content to give more meaning and enjoyment to the job by involving employees in planning, organisation and control of their work, is termed as", "opta": "job enlargement", "optb": "job enrichment", "optc": "job rotation", "optd": "job evaluation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Job enrichment can be described as a medium through which management can motivate self-driven employees by assigning them additional responsibility normally reserved for higher level employees. By doing this, the employees feel like their work has meaning and is important to the company."}, {"question": "Fixed position layout is also known as", "opta": "analytical layout", "optb": "synthetic layout", "optc": "static product layout", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a network shown in the below figure, the critical path is along", "opta": "1-2-3-4-8-9", "optb": "1-2-3-5-6-7-8-9", "optc": "1-2-3-4-7-8-9", "optd": "1-2-5-6-7-8-9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bar chart is suitable for", "opta": "large project", "optb": "major work", "optc": "minor work", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following chart gives simultaneously information about the progress of work and machine loading?", "opta": "Process chart", "optb": "Machine load chart", "optc": "Man-machine chart", "optd": "Gantt chart", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Probabilistic time for completion of any activity can be found out from", "opta": "optimistic time", "optb": "pessimistic time", "optc": "most likely time", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Line organisation is suitable for a big organisation.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PERT is an event oriented technique.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Linear programming model can be applied to line balancing problem and transportation problem.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chart which gives an estimate about the amount of materials handling between various work stations is known as", "opta": "flow chart", "optb": "process chart", "optc": "travel chart", "optd": "operation chart", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of organisation preferred for a steel industry, is", "opta": "line organisation", "optb": "functional organisation", "optc": "line and staff organisation", "optd": "line, staff and functional organisation", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A device used for lifting or lowering objects suspended from a hook at the end of retractable chains or cable is called", "opta": "hoist", "optb": "jib crane", "optc": "portable elevator", "optd": "chain conveyor", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A diagram showing the path followed by men and materials while performing a task is known as", "opta": "string diagram", "optb": "flow process chart", "optc": "travel chart", "optd": "flow diagram", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The determination of standard time in a complex job system is best done through", "opta": "stop watch time study", "optb": "analysis of micromotions", "optc": "grouping timing technique", "optd": "analysis of standard data system", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In CPM, the cost slope is determined by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If (R) is the base rate guaranteed per hour, (S) is the standard time for the job and (T) is the actual time, then according to Rowan plan, wages for the job will be", "opta": "TR", "optb": "", "optc": "TR + (S - T)R", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a line organisation", "opta": "responsibility of each individual is fixed", "optb": "discipline is strong", "optc": "quick decisions are taken", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following are the guidelines for the construction of a network diagram?", "opta": "Each activity is represented by one and only one arrow in the network.", "optb": "Dangling must be avoided in a network diagram.", "optc": "Dummy activity consumes no time or resource.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work study involues", "opta": "only method study", "optb": "only work measurement", "optc": "method study and work measurement", "optd": "only motion study", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A-B-C analysis is used in", "opta": "CPM", "optb": "PERT", "optc": "inventory control", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PERT analysis is based upon", "opta": "optimistic time", "optb": "pessimistic time", "optc": "most likely time", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to avoid excessive multiplication of facilities, the layout preferred is", "opta": "product layout", "optb": "process layout", "optc": "group layout", "optd": "static layout", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In A-B-C analysis, which class of items are generally large in number?", "opta": "A", "optb": "B", "optc": "C", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Simplex method is the method used for", "opta": "value analysis", "optb": "network analysis", "optc": "linear programming", "optd": "queuing theory", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dispatching", "opta": "prescribes the sequence of operations to be followed", "optb": "determines the programme for the operations", "optc": "is concerned with the starting of processes", "optd": "regulates the progress of job through various processes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following wage incentive plan guarantees minimum wage to a worker and bonus is paid for the fixed percentage of time saved?", "opta": "Halsey plan", "optb": "Gantt plan", "optc": "Rowan plan", "optd": "Emerson's efficiency plan", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Job evaluation is the method of determining the", "opta": "relative values of a job", "optb": "worker's performance on a job", "optc": "worth of the machine", "optd": "value of overall production", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The routing function in a production system design is concerned with", "opta": "manpower utilisation", "optb": "quality assurance of the product", "optc": "machine utilisation", "optd": "optimising material flow through the plant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In big automobile repair shop, for elevating and moving the heavy parts such as complete engine assembly, gear box etc., an overhead crane and a fork lift truck is used.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Direct expenses include", "opta": "factory expenses", "optb": "selling expenses", "optc": "administrative expenses", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "String diagram is used", "opta": "for checking the relative values of various layouts", "optb": "when a group of workers are working at a place", "optc": "where processes require the operator to be moved from one work place to another", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following type of layout is suitable for automobile manufacturing concern?", "opta": "product layout", "optb": "process layout", "optc": "fixed position layout", "optd": "combination layout", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Representative time is the average of times recorded by work study man for an operation.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Queuing theory is associated with", "opta": "inventory", "optb": "sales", "optc": "waiting time", "optd": "production time", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PERT requires", "opta": "single time estimate", "optb": "double time estimate", "optc": "triple time estimate", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "A-B-C analysis is based on Pareto's principle.", "optb": "Simulation can be used for inventory control.", "optc": "Economic order quantity formula ignores variations in demand pattern", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The product layout is more amenable to automation than process layout.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In break even analysis, total cost consists of", "opta": "fixed cost + sales revenue", "optb": "variable cost + sales revenue", "optc": "fixed cost + variable cost", "optd": "fixed cost + variable cost + profit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sleeve or muff coupling is designed as a", "opta": "dun cylinder", "optb": "thick cylinder", "optc": "solid shaft", "optd": "hollow shaft", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A sliding bearing in which the working surfaces are completely separated from each other by lubricant is called zero film bearing.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Screws used for power transmission should have", "opta": "Low efficiency", "optb": "high efficiency", "optc": "very fine threads", "optd": "strong teeth", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of rivets in shear shall be equal to the number of rivets in crushing.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When bevel gears connect two shafts whose axes intersect at an angle greater than a right angle and one of the bevel gears has a pitch angle of 90\u00b0, then they are known as", "opta": "angular bevel gears", "optb": "crown bevel gears", "optc": "internal bevel gears", "optd": "mitre gears", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The toughness of a material __________ when it is heated.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of slots in a 25 mm castle nut is", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "6", "optd": "8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A screw is said to be over hauling screw, if its efficiency is", "opta": "less than 50%", "optb": "more than 50%", "optc": "equal to 50%", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The application of third type levers is found in", "opta": "handle of a hand pump", "optb": "hand wheel of a punching press", "optc": "lever of a loaded safety valve", "optd": "a pair of tongs", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For unequal width of butt straps, the thickness of butt straps are", "opta": "0.75 t for wide strap on the inside and 0.625 t for narrow strap on the outside", "optb": "0.75 t for narrow strap on the inside and 0.625 t for wide strap on the outside", "optc": "0.75 t for both the straps on the inside and outside", "optd": "0.625 t for both the straps on the inside and outside", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In second type of levers,", "opta": "load is in between the fulcrum and effort", "optb": "effort is in between the fulcrum and load", "optc": "fulcrum is in between the load and effort", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Soderberg relation is based on __________ of the material whereas all other failure relation for dynamic loading are based on ultimate strength of the material.", "opta": "elastic strength", "optb": "yield strength", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a flange coupling, the flanges are coupled together by means of", "opta": "bolts and nuts", "optb": "studs", "optc": "headless taper bolts", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A transmission shaft includes", "opta": "counter shaft", "optb": "line shaft", "optc": "over head shaft", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to I.B.R., shearing resistance required to shear off the rivet per pitch length (in double shear) is (where n = Number of rivets per pitch length)", "opta": "d2 x \u03c4 x n", "optb": "1.875 x d2 x \u03c4 x n", "optc": "2 x d2 x \u03c4 x n", "optd": "3 x d2x \u03c4 x n", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A locking device in which the bottom cylindrical portion is recessed to receive the tip of the locking set screw, is called", "opta": "castle nut", "optb": "jam nut", "optc": "ring nut", "optd": "sawn nut", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Slenderness ratio is the ratio of", "opta": "maximum size of column to minimum size of column", "optb": "width of column to depth of column", "optc": "effective length of column to least radius of gyration of the column", "optd": "effective length of column to width of column", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A crankshaft is a __________ shaft.", "opta": "transmission", "optb": "machine", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Indian standard specifications, 100 H6/g5 means that the", "opta": "actual size is 100 mm", "optb": "basic size is 100 mm", "optc": "difference between the actual size and basic size is 100 mm", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A plate with an elliptical hole in the centre, with semi-major axis (a) perpendicular to the direction of loading and semi-minor axis (b) along the direction of loading, is subjected to a pull P. The maximum stress induced at the edge of the hole is equal to (where \u03c3 = Stress for a plate with no hole i.e. nominal stress)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity of sliding __________ the distance of the point of contact from the pitch point.", "opta": "is directly proportional to", "optb": "is inversely proportional to", "optc": "is equal to cos \u03c6 multiplied by", "optd": "does not depend upon", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A column is known as a long column if the slenderness ratio is", "opta": "40", "optb": "50", "optc": "70", "optd": "100", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Circumferential joint in boilers is used to get the required length of a boiler.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ball bearings are provided with a cage", "opta": "to reduce friction", "optb": "to facilitate slipping of balls", "optc": "to prevent the lubricant from flowing out", "optd": "to maintain the balls at a fixed distance apart", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When screw threads are to be used in a situation where power is being transmitted in one direction only, then the screw threads suitable for this will be", "opta": "square threads", "optb": "acme threads", "optc": "knuckle threads", "optd": "buttress threads", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In radial cams, the follower moves", "opta": "in a direction perpendicular to the cam axis", "optb": "in a direction parallel to the cam axis", "optc": "in any direction irrespective of cam axis", "optd": "along the cam axis", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The square threads are not so strong as V-threads but they offer less frictional resistance to motion than Whitworth threads.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Unwin's formula, the relation between the diameter of rivet hole (d) and the thickness of plate (t) is given by (where d and t are in mm)", "opta": "d = t", "optb": "d = 1.6 t", "optc": "d = 2 t", "optd": "d = 6 t", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to avoid tearing of the plate at an edge, the distance from the centre line of the rivet hole to the nearest edge of the plate should be equal to (where d = Diameter of rivet hole)", "opta": "d", "optb": "1.5 d", "optc": "2 d", "optd": "2.5 d", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of stress concentration factor depends upon", "opta": "material of the part", "optb": "geometry of the part", "optc": "material and geometry of the part", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following material has the maximum ductility?", "opta": "Mild steel", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Zinc", "optd": "Aluminium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a bolt is subjected to shock loading, the resilience of the bolt should be considered in order to prevent breakage at the", "opta": "head", "optb": "shank", "optc": "thread", "optd": "middle", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to obtain the bolts of uniform strength, an axial hole is drilled through the head as far as the threaded portion such that the area of shank becomes equal to the root area of the thread.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An open belt drive is used when", "opta": "shafts are arranged parallel and rotate in the opposite directions", "optb": "shafts are arranged parallel and rotate in the same directions", "optc": "shafts are arranged at right angles and rotate in one definite direction", "optd": "driven shaft is to be started or stopped whenever desired without interferring with the driving shaft", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In unilateral system of tolerance, the tolerance is allowed on", "opta": "one side of the actual size", "optb": "one side of the nominal size", "optc": "both sides of the actual size", "optd": "both sides of the nominal size", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The constant factor in case of R10 series of preferred numbers is", "opta": "1.06", "optb": "1.12", "optc": "1.26", "optd": "1.58", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pipe joint mostly used for pipes carrying water at low pressures is", "opta": "socket joint", "optb": "nipple joint", "optc": "union joint", "optd": "spigot and socket joint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Guest's theory, the failure occurs at a point in a member when the maximum shear stress in a bi-axial stress system reaches the shear stress at elastic limit in simple tension test.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For maximum power, the velocity of the belt will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Surface endurance limit of gear material is dependent upon its", "opta": "elastic strength", "optb": "yield strength", "optc": "brinell hardness number", "optd": "toughness", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a hydrodynamic lubricated bearing", "opta": "there is a thick film of lubricant between the journal and the bearing", "optb": "there is a thin film of lubricant between the journal and the bearing", "optc": "there is no lubricant between the journal and the bearing", "optd": "the lubricant is forced between the journal and the bearing, by external pressure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct for gears?", "opta": "The addendum is less than dedendum", "optb": "The pitch circle diameter is equal to the product of module and number of teeth", "optc": "The pitch circle is always greater than the base circle", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A flanged pipe joint will be a leak-proof joint, if the circumferential pitch of the bolts is (where d = Diameter of bolt hole)", "opta": "less than 20 d", "optb": "greater than 30 d", "optc": "between 20 d and 30 d", "optd": "equal to inside diameter of pipe", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stress concentration is caused due to", "opta": "variations in load acting on a member", "optb": "variations in properties of materials in a member", "optc": "abrupt change of cross-section", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The resistance to fatigue of a material is measured by", "opta": "elastic limit", "optb": "Young's modulus", "optc": "ultimate tensile strength", "optd": "endurance limit", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The load cup of a screw jack is made separate from the head of the spindle to", "opta": "enhance the load carrying capacity of the jack", "optb": "reduce the effort needed for lifting the working load", "optc": "prevent the rotation of load being lifted", "optd": "reduce the value of frictional torque", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two shafts A and B under pure torsion are of identical length and identical weight and are made of the same material. The shaft A is solid and the shaft B is hollow. We can say that", "opta": "shaft B is better than shaft A", "optb": "shaft A is better than shaft B", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre distance between two meshing involute gears is equal to", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong ?", "opta": "The power transmitted by V-belts is less than flat belts for the same coefficient of friction, arc of contact and allowable tension in the belts", "optb": "The V-belt drive is used with large centre distance", "optc": "The V-belt may be operated in either direction with tight side of the belt at the top or bottom", "optd": "The ratio of driving tensions in V-belt drive is more than flat belt drives", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a flange coupling, the thickness of flanges is taken as one-half the diameter of shaft.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Segmental chips are formed during machining", "opta": "mild steel", "optb": "cast iron", "optc": "high speed steel", "optd": "high carbon steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cemented carbide tool tips are produced by powder metallurgy.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the diameter of the hole is subject to considerable variation, then for locating in jigs and fixtures, the pressure type of locator used is", "opta": "conical locator", "optb": "cylindrical locator", "optc": "diamond pin locator", "optd": "vee locator", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Side rake angle of a single point cutting tool is the angle", "opta": "by which the face of the tool is inclined towards back", "optb": "by which the face of the tool is inclined sideways", "optc": "between the surface of the flank immediately below the point and a plane at right angles to the centre line of the point of the tool", "optd": "between the surface of the flank immediately below the point and a line drawn from the point perpendicular to the base", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Internal gears can be made by", "opta": "hobbing", "optb": "shaping with pinion cutter", "optc": "shaping with rack cutter", "optd": "milling", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to prevent tool from rubbing the work __________ on tools are provided.", "opta": "rake angles", "optb": "relief angles", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The silicon carbide abrasive is chiefly used for grinding", "opta": "cemented carbide", "optb": "ceramic", "optc": "cast iron", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Drilling is an example of", "opta": "orthogonal cutting", "optb": "oblique cutting", "optc": "simple cutting", "optd": "uniform cutting", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A round nose tool may be fed eitner from left to right end or from right to left end of the lathe bed.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the cutting edge of the tool is dull, then during machining", "opta": "continuous chips are formed", "optb": "discontinuous chips are formed", "optc": "continuous chips with built-up edge are formed", "optd": "no chips are formed", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fine grained grinding wheel is used to grind hard materials.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron during machining produces", "opta": "continuous chips", "optb": "discontinuous chips", "optc": "continuous chips with built-up-edge", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A single point thread cutting tool should ideally have", "opta": "zero rake angle", "optb": "positive rake angle", "optc": "negative rake angle", "optd": "point angle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The work or surface speed for cylindrical grinding varies from", "opta": "5 to 10 m/min", "optb": "10 to 20 m/min", "optc": "20 to 30 m/min", "optd": "40 to 60 m/min", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cutting tool in a milling machine is mounted on", "opta": "spindle", "optb": "arbor", "optc": "column", "optd": "knee", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tool made of cemented carbide wear out faster at", "opta": "slow speeds", "optb": "medium speeds", "optc": "fast speeds", "optd": "very fast speeds", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A push broach as compared to pull broach", "opta": "has less number of teeth", "optb": "is short and stocky", "optc": "removes less material for each pass of the tool", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Twist drills are made of", "opta": "high speed steel", "optb": "carbon steel", "optc": "stainless steel", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A twist drill is a", "opta": "side cutting tool", "optb": "front cutting tool", "optc": "end cutting tool", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rake angle required to machine brass by high speed steel tool is", "opta": "0\u00b0", "optb": "10\u00b0", "optc": "20\u00b0", "optd": "-10\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lip angle of a single point tool is usually", "opta": "20\u00b0 to 40\u00b0", "optb": "40\u00b0 to 60\u00b0", "optc": "60\u00b0 to 80\u00b0", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The average cutting speed for turning brass with a high speed steel tool is", "opta": "15 to 19 m/min", "optb": "25 to 31 m/min", "optc": "60 to 90 m/min", "optd": "90 to 120 m/min", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum production of small and slender parts is done by", "opta": "watch maker's lathe", "optb": "sliding head stock automatic lathe", "optc": "multispindle automatic lathe", "optd": "capastan lathe", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Side rake angle on tools is provided to control chip flow.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The method of grinding used to produce a straight or tapered surface on a workpiece, is", "opta": "internal cylindrical grinding", "optb": "form grinding", "optc": "external cylindrical grinding", "optd": "surface grinding", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fixture does not guide the tool.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crater wear occurs mainly on the", "opta": "nose part, front relief face and side relief face of the cutting tool", "optb": "face of the cutting tool at a short distance from the cutting edge only", "optc": "cutting edge only", "optd": "front face only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gear lapping is an operation", "opta": "after heat treatment", "optb": "prior to heat treatment", "optc": "for gear reconditioning", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The facing is an operation of", "opta": "bevelling the extreme end of a workpiece", "optb": "embossing a diamond shaped pattern on the surface of a workpiece", "optc": "reducing the diameter of a workpiece over a very narrow surface", "optd": "machining the ends of a workpiece to produce a flat surface square with the axis", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fixture is defined as a device which", "opta": "holds and locates a workpiece and guides and controls one or more cutting tools", "optb": "holds and locates a workpiece during an inspection or for a manufacturing operation", "optc": "is used to check the accuracy of workpiece", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A drill considered as a cutting tool having zero rake, is known as a", "opta": "flat drill", "optb": "straight fluted drill", "optc": "parallel shank twist drill", "optd": "tapered shank twist drill", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong about ultra-sonic machining?", "opta": "It is best suited for machining hard and brittle materials.", "optb": "It cuts materials at very slow speeds.", "optc": "It removes large amount of material.", "optd": "It produces good surface finish.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In oblique cutting system, the maximum chip thickness occurs at the middle.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Larger end cutting edge angle __________ tool life.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lead screw of a lathe has __________ threads.", "opta": "single start", "optb": "double start", "optc": "multi-start", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A left hand tool on a lathe cuts most efficiently when it travels", "opta": "from left to right end of the lathe bed", "optb": "from right to left end of the lathe bed", "optc": "with the help of a compound slide", "optd": "across the bed", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The correct sequence of tool materials in increasing order of their ability to retain their hot hardness is", "opta": "carbide, ceramic, cermet, borazon", "optb": "ceramic, carbide, borazon, cermet", "optc": "cermet, carbide, ceramic, borazon", "optd": "borazon, ceramic, carbide, cermet", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect with reference of lathe cutting tools?", "opta": "The flank of the tool is the surface or surfaces below and adjacent to the cutting edges", "optb": "The nose is the corner, arc or chamfer joining the side cutting and the end cutting edges", "optc": "The heel is that part of the tool which is shaped to produce the cutting edges and face", "optd": "The base is that surface of the shank which bears against the support and takes tangent pressure of the cut", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the relation VTn = C, the value of n for carbide tools is", "opta": "0.1 to 0.2", "optb": "0.20 to 0.25", "optc": "0.25 to 0.40", "optd": "0.40 to 0.55", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In up milling, the thickness of chip is", "opta": "minimum at the beginning of the cut and maximum at the end of the cut", "optb": "maximum at the beginning of the cut and minimum at the end of the cut", "optc": "uniform throughout the cut", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The machining of titanium is difficult due to", "opta": "high thermal conductivity of titanium", "optb": "chemical reaction between tool and work", "optc": "low tool-chip contact area", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In orthogonal cutting system, the maximum chip thickness occurs at the middle.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lapping is an operation of", "opta": "making a cone-shaped enlargement of the end of a hole", "optb": "smoothing and squaring the surface around a hole", "optc": "sizing and finishing a small diameter hole", "optd": "producing a hole by removing metal along the circumference of a hollow cutting tool", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The different spindle speeds on a lathe form", "opta": "arithmetical progression", "optb": "geometrical progression", "optc": "harmonical progression", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the helix angle of the drill is made __________ 30\u00b0, then the torque required to drive the drill at a given feed will be more.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle included between the two lips projected upon a plane parallel to the drill axis and paralled to the two cutting lips, is called helix angle.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In hot machining, tool is made of", "opta": "tungsten carbide", "optb": "brass or copper", "optc": "diamond", "optd": "stainless steel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In ultra-sonic machining, the metal is removed by", "opta": "using abrasive slurry between the tool and work", "optb": "direct contact of tool with the work", "optc": "maintaining an electrolyte between the work and tool in a very small gap between the two", "optd": "erosion caused by rapidly recurring spark discharges between the tool and work", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity of tool relative to the workpiece is known as cutting velocity.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Grinding wheels should be tested for balance", "opta": "only at the time of manufacture", "optb": "before starting the grinding operation", "optc": "at the end of grinding operation", "optd": "occasionally", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The object of producing draught in a boiler is", "opta": "to provide an adequate supply of air for the fuel combustion", "optb": "to exhaust the gases of combustion from the combustion chamber", "optc": "to discharge the gases of combustion to the atmosphere through the chimney", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a glass tube type water indicator for a boiler, one end of the tube is connected to water space and the other end is connected to", "opta": "water space also", "optb": "chimney", "optc": "steam space", "optd": "superheater", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In water tube boilers", "opta": "water passes through the tubes which are surrounded by flames and hot gases", "optb": "the flames and hot gases pass through the tubes which are surrounded by water", "optc": "forced circulation takes place", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong ?", "opta": "Locomotive boiler is a water tube boiler.", "optb": "Water tube boilers are internally fired.", "optc": "La-mont boiler is a low pressure water tube boiler.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A grate, in a boiler, is a place in the combustion chamber upon which fuel (wood or coal) is burnt.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Loeffler boiler is a water tube boiler using a forced circulation of water.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "La-mont boiler, is a high pressure water tube steam boiler working on forced circulation.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a connecting rod is not to convert reciprocating motion of the piston into rotary motion.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct for a compound steam engine ?", "opta": "The cost of the engine, for the same power and economy, is more than that of a simple steam engine.", "optb": "The forces in the working parts are increased as the forces are distributed over more parts.", "optc": "The ratio of expansion is reduced, thus reducing the length of stroke.", "optd": "The temperature range per cylinder is increased, with corresponding increase in condensation.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the speed of the crankshaft is between 100 r.p.m. and 250 r.p.m., the engine said to be a", "opta": "slow speed engine", "optb": "medium speed steam engine", "optc": "high speed steam engine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The natural draught is produced by", "opta": "steam jet", "optb": "centrifugal fan", "optc": "chimney", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Willian's line for the steam engine is a straight line relationship between the steam consumption per hour and", "opta": "indicated power", "optb": "brake power", "optc": "efficiency", "optd": "pressure of steam", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature of condensate is __________ on leaving the condenser than that of circulating water at inlet.", "opta": "higher", "optb": "lower", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A draught produced by a chimney due to the difference of densities between the hot gases inside the chimney and cold atmospheric air outside it, is called natural draught.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct ?", "opta": "A fire tube boiler occupies less space than a water tube boiler, for a given power.", "optb": "Steam at a high pressure and in large quantities can be produced with a simple vertical boiler.", "optc": "A simple vertical boiler has one fire tube.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A device used to increase the temperature of saturated steam without raising its pressure, is called", "opta": "blow off cock", "optb": "fusible plug", "optc": "superheater", "optd": "stop valve", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter of flue tube in a Cornish boiler is __________ that of the shell.", "opta": "one-fourth", "optb": "one-third", "optc": "two-fifth", "optd": "three-fifth", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An economiser __________ the steam raising capacity of a boiler.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fire tube boilers are", "opta": "internally fired", "optb": "externally fired", "optc": "internally as well as externally fired", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A safety valve usually employed with stationary boilers is", "opta": "lever safety valve", "optb": "dead weight safety valve", "optc": "high steam and low water safety valve", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The draught produced by a steam jet issuing from a nozzle placed in the ashpit under the fire grate of the furnace is called", "opta": "induced steam jet draught", "optb": "chimney draught", "optc": "forced steam jet draught", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is wrong ?", "opta": "The factor of evaporation for all boilers is always greater than unity.", "optb": "The amount of water evaporated in kg per kg of fuel burnt is called equivalent evaporation from and at 100\u00b0 C.", "optc": "The ratio of heat actually used in producing the steam to the heat liberated in the furnace is called boiler efficiency.", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a crosshead is to guide motion of the __________ and to prevent it from bending.", "opta": "piston rod", "optb": "connecting rod", "optc": "eccentric rod", "optd": "valve rod", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cylinder dimensions of a compound engine may be designed on the basis of", "opta": "equal power developed in each cylinder for uniform turning moment", "optb": "equal initial piston loads on all pistons for obtaining same size of piston rod, connecting rod etc. for all cylinders", "optc": "equal temperature drop in each cylinder for economy of steam", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a piston rod is", "opta": "to guide motion of the piston rod and to prevent it from bending", "optb": "to transfer motion from the piston to the cross head", "optc": "to convert heat energy of the steam into mechanical work", "optd": "to exhust steam from the cylinder at proper moment", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An air preheater is installed", "opta": "before the economiser", "optb": "before the superheater", "optc": "between the economiser and chimney", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The length of shell of a Locomotive boiler is", "opta": "1 m", "optb": "2 m", "optc": "3 m", "optd": "4 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The effect of wire drawing is to decrease the area of indicator diagram and thus work done by the engine is reduced.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a uniflow engine", "opta": "steam enters and exhausts through the same port", "optb": "steam enters at one end and exhausts at the centre", "optc": "steam enters at the centre and exhausts at the other end", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shell diameter of a Locomotive boiler is", "opta": "1 m", "optb": "1.5 m", "optc": "2 m", "optd": "2.5 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fire tubes in a Scotch marine boiler are", "opta": "horizontal", "optb": "vertical", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reciprocating steam engine, the heat energy in the steam is converted into mechanical work by the to and fro motion of the piston.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The power of a boiler may be defined as", "opta": "the ratio of heat actually used in producing the steam to the heat liberated in the furnace", "optb": "the amount of water evaporated or steam produced in kg per kg of fuel burnt", "optc": "the amount of water evaporated from and at 100\u00b0 C into dry and saturated steam", "optd": "the evaporation of 15.653 kg of water per hour from and at 100\u00b0 C", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the circulation of water, in a boiler, is by a centrifugal pump, then the boiler is known as", "opta": "internally fired boiler", "optb": "externally fired boiler", "optc": "natural circulation boiler", "optd": "forced circulation boiler", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a safety valve is", "opta": "to blow off steam when the pressure of steam inside the boiler exceeds the working pressure", "optb": "to indicate the water level inside the boiler to an observer", "optc": "to measure pressure of steam inside the steam boiler", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fire tubes in a Cochran boiler are", "opta": "horizontal", "optb": "vertical", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A double acting steam engine with a cylinder diameter of 190 mm and a stroke of 300 mm has a cut-off of 0.35. The expansion ratio for this engine is nearly", "opta": "1.05", "optb": "2.86", "optc": "6.65", "optd": "10.05", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The aim of a compound steam engine is", "opta": "to reduce the ratio of expansion in each cylinder", "optb": "to reduce the length of stroke", "optc": "to reduce the temperature range in each cylinder", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The average operating pressure of Benson boiler is", "opta": "100 bar", "optb": "150 bar", "optc": "200 bar", "optd": "250 bar", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter of Cornish boiler varies from", "opta": "0.5 to 1 m", "optb": "1 to 2 m", "optc": "1.25 to 2.5 m", "optd": "2 to 3 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A single acting steam engine produces __________ power than that of double acting steam engine.", "opta": "equal", "optb": "half", "optc": "double", "optd": "four times", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure of steam in the engine cylinder at the beginning of the stroke is __________ the boiler pressure.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a flywheel is", "opta": "to convert reciprocating motion of the piston into rotary motion.", "optb": "to convert rotary motion of the crankshaft into to and fro motion of the valve rod", "optc": "to prevent fluctuation of speed", "optd": "to keep the engine speed uniform at all load conditions", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of steam produced in Benson boiler is", "opta": "100 tonnes/h", "optb": "135 tonnes/h", "optc": "175 tonnes/h", "optd": "250 tonnes/h", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In natural circulation steam boilers, the circulation of water is by convection currents which are set up during the heating of water.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cut-off governing of steam engines is a method of controlling the engine output by varying", "opta": "volume of intake steam", "optb": "pressure of intake steam", "optc": "temperature of intake steam", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a boiler, feed water supplied per hour is 205 kg while coal fired per hour is 23 kg. The net enthalpy rise per kg of water is 145 kJ. If the calorific valve of the coal is 2050 kJ/kg, then the boiler efficiency will be", "opta": "56%", "optb": "63%", "optc": "74%", "optd": "78%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A safety valve mainly used with locomotive and marine boilers is", "opta": "lever safety valve", "optb": "dead weight safety valve", "optc": "high steam and low water safety valve", "optd": "spring loaded safety valve", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following boiler is best suited to meet the fluctuating demand of steam ?", "opta": "Locomotive boiler", "optb": "Lancashire boiler", "optc": "Cornish boiler", "optd": "Babcock and Wilcox boiler", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct ?", "opta": "Lancashire boiler is a fire tube boiler.", "optb": "Fire tube boilers are internally fired.", "optc": "Babcock and Wilcox boiler is a water tube boiler.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A nozzle is said to be a convergent nozzle", "opta": "when the cross-section of the nozzle increases continuously from entrance to exit", "optb": "when the cross-section of the nozzle decreases continuously from entrance to exit", "optc": "when the cross-section of the nozzle first decreases from entrance to throat and then increases from its throat to exit", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A turbine is said to have an axial discharge when the steam leaves the blade tip at __________ to the direction of the blade motion.", "opta": "60\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "180\u00b0", "optd": "270\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The flow through a nozzle is regarded as", "opta": "constant volume flow", "optb": "constant pressure flow", "optc": "isothermal flow", "optd": "isentropic flow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of total useful heat drop to the total isentropic heat drop, is called", "opta": "stage efficiency", "optb": "internal efficiency", "optc": "Rankine efficiency", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure at which the steam leaves the nozzle is known as back pressure.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of steam in a convergent-divergent nozzle __________ after the throat (i.e. in the divergent portion of the nozzle)", "opta": "remains constant", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of discharge through the nozzle __________ when the exit pressure is gradually reduced.", "opta": "remains same", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity of steam leaving the nozzle (V) is given by (where K = Nozzle coefficient or nozzle efficiency, and hd = Enthalpy or heat drop during expansion of steam in a nozzle)", "opta": "V = 44.72 hd K", "optb": "V = 44.72 K hd", "optc": "V = 44.72 K hd", "optd": "V = 44.72 K hd", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a nozzle, whole frictional loss is assumed to occur between", "opta": "inlet and thoroat", "optb": "inlet and outlet", "optc": "throat and exit", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio for initially wet steam is", "opta": "0.546", "optb": "0.577", "optc": "0.582", "optd": "0.601", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The isentropic enthalpy drop in moving blade is two-third of the isentropic enthalpy drop in fixed blades of a turbine. The degree of reaction will be", "opta": "0.4", "optb": "0.56", "optc": "0.67", "optd": "1.67", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The impulse reaction turbine has its driving force", "opta": "as an impulsive force", "optb": "as a reaction force", "optc": "partly as an impulsive force and partly as a reaction force", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of reaction turbine is maximum when (where \u03b1 = Angle made by the absolute velocity (V) at inlet)", "opta": "Vb = 0.5 V cos \u03b1", "optb": "Vb = V cos \u03b1", "optc": "Vb = 0.5 V2 cos \u03b1", "optd": "Vb = V2 cos \u03b1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A regenerative steam cycle renders", "opta": "increased work output per unit mass of steam", "optb": "decreased work output per unit mass of steam", "optc": "increased thermal efficiency", "optd": "decreased work output per unit mass of steam as well as increased thermal efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "De-Laval turbine is a", "opta": "single rotor impulse turbine", "optb": "multi-rotor impulse turbine", "optc": "impulse reaction turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine, in which the general direction of the steam flow is parallel to the turbine axis, is called axial flow turbines", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure gives the velocity of steam at the throat equal to the velocity of sound.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reheat factor is the ratio of the", "opta": "cumulative heat drop to the isentropic heat drop", "optb": "isentropic heat drop to the heat supplied", "optc": "total useful heat drop to the total isentropic heat drop", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine blades do not change the direction of steam issuing from the nozzle.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal equilibrium means that the flow of steam is", "opta": "isothermal", "optb": "isentropic", "optc": "hyperbolic", "optd": "polytropic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the back pressure of a nozzle is below the designed value of pressure at exit of nozzle, the nozzle is said to be", "opta": "choked", "optb": "underdamping", "optc": "overdamping", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the workdone on the blades to the energy supplied to the blades, is called", "opta": "blading efficiency", "optb": "nozzle efficiency", "optc": "gross or stage efficiency", "optd": "mechanical efficiency", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge is __________ at critical pressure.", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The supersaturated flow of steam through a nozzle as compared to a stable flow, the available heat drop", "opta": "remains the same", "optb": "increases", "optc": "decreases", "optd": "is unpredictable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steam leaves the nozzle at a", "opta": "high pressure and a low velocity", "optb": "high pressure and a high velocity", "optc": "low pressure and a low velocity", "optd": "low pressure and a high velocity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure gives the velocity of steam at the throat", "opta": "equal to the velocity of sound", "optb": "less than the velocity of sound", "optc": "more than the velocity of sound", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Parsons' reaction turbine has", "opta": "only moving blades", "optb": "only fixed blades", "optc": "identical fixed and moving blades", "optd": "fixed and moving blades of different shape", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The action of steam in a steam turbine is", "opta": "static", "optb": "dynamic", "optc": "static and dynamic", "optd": "neither static nor dynamic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The blade velocity coefficient is ratio of relative velocity of steam at outlet tip of the blade to the relative velocity of steam at inlet tip of the blade.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Multi-stage steam turbines are of the", "opta": "velocity compounded type", "optb": "reaction type", "optc": "pressure compounded type", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio (p2/p1) is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In reaction turbines, the axial thrust is due to", "opta": "pressure drop across the rotor", "optb": "change in axial velocity", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The expansion of steam in a nozzle follows Rankine cycle.", "optb": "The friction in the nozzle increases the dryness fraction of steam.", "optc": "The pressure of steam at throat is called critical pressure.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A binary vapour plant consists of", "opta": "steam turbine", "optb": "steam condenser", "optc": "mercury boiler", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a De-Laval nozzle expanding superheated steam from 10 bar to 0.1 bar, the pressure at the minimum cross-section (i. e. pressure at throat, p2) will be", "opta": "3.3 bar", "optb": "5.46 bar", "optc": "8.2 bar", "optd": "9.9 bar", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stage efficiency (\u03b7S) is given by (where \u03b7B = Blading efficiency, and \u03b7N = Nozzle efficiency)", "opta": "\u03b7S = \u03b7B x \u03b7N", "optb": "\u03b7S = \u03b7B/\u03b7N", "optc": "\u03b7S = \u03b7N/\u03b7B", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical pressure ratio for initially dry saturated steam is more as compared to initially wet steam.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a convergent divergent nozzle, the discharge depends upon the initial conditions of steam and the area of nozzle at throat.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Parson's reaction turbine is a __________ reaction turbine.", "opta": "40 percent", "optb": "50 percent", "optc": "60 percent", "optd": "70 percent", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The turbine blades are", "opta": "straight", "optb": "circular", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The variation of steam pressure in the nozzle depends upon", "opta": "velocity of steam", "optb": "specific volume of steam", "optc": "dryness fraction of steam", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam turbines are used for", "opta": "large marine propulsion", "optb": "electric power generation", "optc": "direct drive of fans, compressors, pumps", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Parson's turbine is a", "opta": "simple impulse turbine", "optb": "simple reaction turbine", "optc": "impulse-reaction turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of the reheat factor varies from", "opta": "1.02 to 1.06", "optb": "1.08 to 1.l0", "optc": "1.2 to 1.6", "optd": "1.6 to 2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steam enters the nozzle at a", "opta": "high pressure and a low velocity", "optb": "high pressure and a high velocity", "optc": "low pressure and a low velocity", "optd": "low pressure and a high velocity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of supersaturated temperature and saturation temperature at that pressure is called", "opta": "degree of supersaturation", "optb": "degree of superheat", "optc": "degree of undercooling", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum efficiency of a reaction turbine is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the useful heat drop to the isentropic heat drop is called", "opta": "condenser efficiency", "optb": "nozzle efficiency", "optc": "boiler efficiency", "optd": "vacuum efficiency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of steam turbines may be improved by", "opta": "reheating of steam", "optb": "regenerative feed heating", "optc": "binary vapour plant", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, when steam flows through the fixed blades,", "opta": "pressure increases while velocity decreases", "optb": "pressure decreases while velocity increases", "optc": "pressure and velocity both decreases", "optd": "pressure and velocity both increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Strain energy is the", "opta": "energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limits", "optb": "energy stored in a body when strained upto the breaking of a specimen", "optc": "maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body", "optd": "proof resilience per unit volume of a material", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A vertical column has two moments of inertia (i.e. Ixx and Iyy ). The column will tend to buckle in the direction of the", "opta": "axis of load", "optb": "perpendicular to the axis of load", "optc": "maximum moment of inertia", "optd": "minimum moment of inertia", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The neutral axis of the cross-section a beam is that axis at which the bending stress is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Euler's formula holds good only for", "opta": "short columns", "optb": "long columns", "optc": "both short and long columns", "optd": "weak columns", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The object of caulking in a riveted joint is to make the joint", "opta": "free from corrosion", "optb": "stronger in tension", "optc": "free from stresses", "optd": "leak-proof", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steel bar of 5 mm is heated from 15\u00b0 C to 40\u00b0 C and it is free to expand. The bar Will induce", "opta": "no stress", "optb": "shear stress", "optc": "tensile stress", "optd": "compressive stress", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A body is subjected to a tensile stress of 1200 MPa on one plane and another tensile stress of 600 MPa on a plane at right angles to the former. It is also subjected to a shear stress of 400 MPa on the same planes. The maximum normal stress will be", "opta": "400 MPa", "optb": "500 MPa", "optc": "900 MPa", "optd": "1400 MPa", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two shafts 'A' and 'B' transmit the same power. The speed of shaft 'A' is 250 r.p.m. and that of shaft 'B' is 300 r.p.m. The shaft 'B' has the greater diameter.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A thick cylindrical shell having ro and ri as outer and inner radii, is subjected to an internal pressure (p). The maximum tangential stress at the inner surface of the shell is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stress induced in a body, when suddenly loaded, is __________ the stress induced when the same load is applied gradually.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "one-half", "optc": "twice", "optd": "four times", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a beam, as shown in the below figure, the maximum deflection is .", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the slenderness ratio for a column is 100, then it is said to be a __________ column.", "opta": "long", "optb": "medium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A masonry dam may fail due to", "opta": "tension in the masonry of the dam and its base", "optb": "overturning of the dam", "optc": "crushing of masonry at the base of the dam", "optd": "any one of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to prevent crushing of masonry at the base of the dam, the maximum stress should be __________ the permissible stress of the soil.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body is subjected to two equal and opposite pushes, as a result of which the body tends to reduce its length, the stress and strain induced is compressive.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bending moment at a point on a beam is the algebraic __________ of all the moments on either side of the point.", "opta": "sum", "optb": "difference", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum diameter of the hole that can be punched from a plate of maximum shear stress 1/4th of its maximum crushing stress of punch, is equal to (where t = Thickness of the plate)", "opta": "t", "optb": "2t", "optc": "4t", "optd": "8t", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two closely coiled helical springs 'A' and 'B' are equal in all respects but the number of turns of spring 'A' is half that of spring 'B' The ratio of deflections in spring 'A' to spring 'B' is", "opta": "1/8", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deformation per unit length is called", "opta": "tensile stress", "optb": "compressive stress", "optc": "shear stress", "optd": "strain", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A thin cylindrical shell of diameter (d) and thickness (t) is subjected to an internal pressure (p). The ratio of longitudinal strain to volumetric strain is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the torsion equation  the term J/R is called", "opta": "shear modulus", "optb": "section modulus", "optc": "polar modulus", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Strain resetters are used to", "opta": "measure shear strain", "optb": "measure linear strain", "optc": "measure volumetric strain", "optd": "relieve strain", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The torque transmitted by a solid shaft of diameter (D) is (where \u03c4 = Maximum allowable shear stress)", "opta": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optb": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optc": "x \u03c4 x D3", "optd": "x \u03c4 x D3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a rectangular beam is loaded transversely, the maximum compressive stress is developed on the", "opta": "top layer", "optb": "bottom layer", "optc": "neutral axis", "optd": "every cross-section", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a beam, as shown in the below figure, when the load W is applied in the centre of the beam, the maximum deflection is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The point of contraflexure is a point where", "opta": "shear force changes sign", "optb": "bending moment changes sign", "optc": "shear force is maximum", "optd": "bending moment is maximum", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The simply supported beam 'A' of length l carries a central point load W. Another beam 'B' is loaded with a uniformly distributed load such that the total load on the beam is W. The ratio of maximum deflections between beams A and B is", "opta": "5/8", "optb": "8/5", "optc": "5/4", "optd": "4/5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum stress produced in a bar of tapering section is at", "opta": "smaller end", "optb": "larger end", "optc": "middle", "optd": "anywhere", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limit is known as", "opta": "resilience", "optb": "proof resilience", "optc": "strain energy", "optd": "impact energy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In compression test, the fracture in cast iron specimen would occur along", "opta": "the axis of load", "optb": "an oblique plane", "optc": "at right angles to the axis of specimen", "optd": "would not occur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bending stress in a beam is __________ section modulus.", "opta": "directly proportional to", "optb": "inversely proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When shear force at a point is zero, then bending moment is __________ at that point.", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum bending moment for the beam shown in the below figure, lies at a distance of __________ from the end B.", "opta": "l/2", "optb": "l/3", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a bar is cooled to - 5\u00b0C, it will develop", "opta": "no stress", "optb": "shear stress", "optc": "tensile stress", "optd": "compressive stress", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The limit of eccentricity is based upon no tension condition.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to know whether a column is long or short, we must know its slenderness ratio.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A composite shaft consisting of two stepped portions having spring constants k1 and k2 is held between two rigid supports at the ends. Its equivalent spring constant is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "k1+k2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resilience is the", "opta": "energy stored in a body when strained within elastic limits", "optb": "energy stored in a body when strained upto the breaking of the specimen", "optc": "maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the depth is kept constant for a beam of uniform strength, then its width will vary in proportional to (where M = Bending moment)", "opta": "M", "optb": "M", "optc": "M2", "optd": "M3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A concentrated load is one which", "opta": "acts at a point on a beam", "optb": "spreads non-uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "optc": "spreads uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "optd": "varies uniformly over the whole length of a beam", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the tearing efficiency of a riveted joint is 50%, then ratio of rivet hole diameter to the pitch of rivets is", "opta": "0.20", "optb": "0.30", "optc": "0.50", "optd": "0.60", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rectangular beam 'A' has length l, width b and depth d. Another beam 'B' has the same length and depth but width is double that of 'A'. The elastic strength of beam 'B' will be __________ as compared to beam A.", "opta": "same", "optb": "double", "optc": "four times", "optd": "six times", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a simple bending of beams, the stress in the beam varies", "opta": "linearly", "optb": "parabolically", "optc": "hyperbolically", "optd": "elliptically", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A beam supported at its both ends is not a simply supported beam.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stress at which the extension of the material takes place more quickly as compared to the increase in load, is called", "opta": "elastic limit", "optb": "yield point", "optc": "ultimate point", "optd": "breaking point", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The strain energy stored in a solid circular shaft subjected to shear stress (\u03c4) is (where C = Modulus of rigidity for the shaft material)", "opta": "x Volume of shaft", "optb": "x Volume of shaft", "optc": "x Volume of shaft", "optd": "x Volume of shaft", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When two main plates are kept in alignment butting each other and riveted with cover plate on both sides of the main plates with two rows of rivets in each main plate, the joint is known as __________ double cover butt joint.", "opta": "single riveted", "optb": "double riveted", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Whenever a material is loaded within elastic limit, stress is __________ strain.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "directly proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A load which is spread over a beam in such a manner that it varies uniformly over the whole length of abeam is called uniformly __________ load.", "opta": "distributed", "optb": "varying", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "The energy stored in a body, when strained within elastic limit is known as strain energy.", "optb": "The maximum strain energy which can be stored in a body is termed as proof resilience.", "optc": "The proof resilience per unit volume of a material is known as modulus of resilience.", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the actual damping coefficient to the critical damping coefficient is called damping factor.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body moves with simple harmonic motion, the product of its periodic time and frequency is equal to", "opta": "zero", "optb": "one", "optc": "\u03c0/2", "optd": "\u03c0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a vibrating system, if the actual damping coefficient is 40 N/m/s and critical damping coefficient is 420 N/m/s, then logarithmic decrement is equal to", "opta": "0.2", "optb": "0.4", "optc": "0.6", "optd": "0.8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For high speed engines, the cam follower should move with", "opta": "uniform velocity", "optb": "simple harmonic motion", "optc": "uniform acceleration and retardation", "optd": "cycloidal motion", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a coupling rod of a locomotive, each of the four pairs is a __________ pair.", "opta": "sliding", "optb": "turning", "optc": "rolling", "optd": "screw", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03c9/\u03c9n is very high for a body vibrating under steady state vibrations, the phase angle for all values of damping factors, will tend to approach", "opta": "0\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "180\u00b0", "optd": "360\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a circular arc cam with roller follower, the acceleration in any position of the lift will depend only upon", "opta": "total lift, total angle of lift, minimum radius of cam and cam speed", "optb": "radius of circular arc, cam speed, location of centre of circular arc and roller diameter", "optc": "mass of cam follower linkage, spring stiffness and cam speed", "optd": "total lift, centre of gravity of the cam and cam speed", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the relation between the controlling force (Fc) and radius of rotation (r) for a spring controlled governor is Fc = ar + b, then the governor will be", "opta": "stable", "optb": "unstable", "optc": "isochronous", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The factor which affects the critical speed of a shaft is", "opta": "diameter of disc", "optb": "span of shaft", "optc": "eccentricity", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The partial balancing of reciprocating parts in locomotives produces", "opta": "hammer blow", "optb": "swaying couple", "optc": "variation in tractive force along the line of stroke", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pair is known as a higher pair, when the relative motion between the elements of a pair is", "opta": "turning only", "optb": "sliding only", "optc": "rolling only", "optd": "partly turning and partly sliding", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the connection between the two elements is such that only required kind of relative motion occurs, it is known as self-closed pair.", "opta": "Right", "optb": "Wrong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Whitworth quick return motion mechanism is formed in a slider crank chain when the", "opta": "coupler link is fixed", "optb": "longest link is a fixed link", "optc": "slider is a fixed link", "optd": "smallest link is a fixed link", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The primary unbalanced force is maximum when the angle of inclination of the crank with the line of stroke is", "opta": "0\u00b0 and 90\u00b0", "optb": "0\u00b0 and 180\u00b0", "optc": "90\u00b0 and 180\u00b0", "optd": "180\u00b0 and 360\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The acceleration of the particle moving with simple harmonic motion is inversely proportional to the displacement of the particle from the mean position.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In vibration isolation system, the transmissibility will be equal to unity, for all values of damping factor, if \u03c9/\u03c9n is", "opta": "equal to one", "optb": "equal to 2", "optc": "less than 2", "optd": "greater than 2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The two links OA and OB are connected by a pin joint at O. If the link OA turns with angular velocity \u03c91 rad/s in the clockwise direction and the link OB turns with angular velocity \u03c92 rad/s in the clockwise direction, then the rubbing velocity at the pin joint O is (where r = Radius of the pin at O)", "opta": "\u03c91.\u03c92.r", "optb": "( \u03c91 - \u03c92)r", "optc": "( \u03c91 + \u03c92)r", "optd": "( \u03c91 - \u03c92)2r", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If \u03c9/\u03c9n = 2, where co is the frequency of excitation and \u03c9n is the natural frequency of vibrations, then the transmissibility of vibration will the", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.5", "optd": "2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A disturbing mass m1 attached to the rotating shaft may be balanced by a single mass m2 attached in the same plane of rotation as that of m1, such that (where r1 and r2 are the radii of rotation of m1 and m2 respectively)", "opta": "m1r2 = m2r1", "optb": "m1r1 = m2r2", "optc": "m1m2 = r1r2", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In railway axle boxes, the bearing used is", "opta": "deep groove ball bearing", "optb": "double row self-aligning ball bearing", "optc": "double row spherical roller bearing", "optd": "cylindrical roller bearing", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the two elements of a pair have a surface contact when relative motion takes place and the surface of one element slides over the surface of the other, the pair formed is known as a", "opta": "lower pair", "optb": "higher pair", "optc": "self-closed pair", "optd": "force-closed pair", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centre distance between two meshing involute gears is equal to", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The two elements of a pair are said to form a __________ when they permit relative motion between them.", "opta": "open pair", "optb": "kinematic pair", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the axes of the shafts, over which the gears are mounted, move relative to a fixed axis, then the train is known as reverted gear train.", "opta": "Right", "optb": "Wrong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In under damped vibrating system, the amplitude of vibration", "opta": "decreases linearly with time", "optb": "increases linearly with time", "optc": "decreases exponentially with time", "optd": "increases exponentially with time", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dynamic friction is the friction experienced by a body, when the body", "opta": "is in motion", "optb": "is at rest", "optc": "just begins to slide over the surface of the other body", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steering of a ship means", "opta": "movement of a complete ship up and down in vertical plane about transverse axis", "optb": "turning of a complete ship in a curve towards right or left, while it moves forward", "optc": "rolling of a complete ship side-ways", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tractive force in a locomotive with two cylinders is given by (where c = Fraction of reciprocating parts per cylinder, m = Mass of reciprocating parts, \u03c9 = Angular speed of crank, r = Radius of crank, and \u03b8 = Angle of inclination of crank to the line of stroke)", "opta": "m.\u03c92.r cos \u03b8", "optb": "c.m.\u03c92.r sin \u03b8", "optc": "(1 - c)m.\u03c92.r(cos \u03b8 - sin \u03b8)", "optd": "m.\u03c92.r(cos \u03b8 - sin \u03b8)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radial distance of a tooth from the pitch circle to the bottom of the tooth is called", "opta": "dedendum", "optb": "addendum", "optc": "clearance", "optd": "working depth", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the crank is at the inner dead centre, in a reciprocating steam engine, then the velocity of the piston will be", "opta": "minimum", "optb": "zero", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The gears are termed as medium velocity gears, if their peripheral velocity is", "opta": "1 - 3 m/s", "optb": "3 - 15 m/s", "optc": "15 - 30 m/s", "optd": "30 - 50 m/s", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a twin cylinder V-engine, the crank positions for primary reverse cranks and secondary direct cranks are shown in the below figure. The engine is a", "opta": "30\u00b0 V-engine", "optb": "60\u00b0 V-engine", "optc": "120\u00b0 V-engine", "optd": "150\u00b0 V-engine", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The frequency of damped vibrations with viscous damping is __________ the frequency of undamped vibrations.", "opta": "more than", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Whitworth quick return motion mechanism consists of three turning pairs and one sliding pair.", "opta": "Right", "optb": "Wrong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rotor of a ship rotates in clockwise direction when viewed from stern and the ship takes a right turn. The effect of gyroscopic couple acting on it will be to raise the stern and lower the bow.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sliding pairs, turning pairs and screw pairs form lower pairs.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a particle moves round the circumference of a circle of radius r with \u03c9 rad/s, then its maximum acceleration is \u03c92r.", "opta": "Right", "optb": "Wrong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The static friction", "opta": "bears a constant ratio to the normal reaction between the two surfaces", "optb": "is independent of the area of contact, between the two surfaces", "optc": "always acts in a direction, opposite to that in which the body tends to move", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A shaft has an attached disc at the centre of its length. The disc has its centre of gravity located at a distance of 2 mm from the axis of the shaft. When the shaft is allowed to vibrate in its natural bow-shaped mode, it has a frequency of vibration of 10 rad/s. When the shaft is rotated at 300 r.p.m., it will whirl with a radius of", "opta": "2 mm", "optb": "2.22 mm", "optc": "2.50 mm", "optd": "3.0 mm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The swaying couple is maximum or minimum when the angle of inclination of the crank to the line of stroke (\u03b8) is equal to", "opta": "90\u00b0 and 180\u00b0", "optb": "45\u00b0 and 225\u00b0", "optc": "180\u00b0 and 270\u00b0", "optd": "270\u00b0 and 360\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure angle of a cam is the angle between the direction of the follower motion and a normal to the", "opta": "pitch circle", "optb": "base circle", "optc": "pitch curve", "optd": "prime circle", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pair of friction discs is an example of rolling pair.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to balance the reciprocating masses,", "opta": "primary forces and couples must be balanced", "optb": "secondary forces and couples must be balanced", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a screw jack, the effort required to lower the load W is given by", "opta": "P = W tan(\u03b1 - \u03c6)", "optb": "P = W tan(\u03b1 + \u03c6)", "optc": "P = W tan(\u03c6 - \u03b1)", "optd": "P = W cos(\u03b1 + \u03c6)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An automobile steering gear is an example of", "opta": "sliding pair", "optb": "rolling pair", "optc": "lower pair", "optd": "higher pair", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The frictional torque transmitted in a multi-collared shaft is same as that of a single collared shaft.", "opta": "Right", "optb": "Wrong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to give the primary balance of the reciprocating parts of a multi-cylinder in-line engines,", "opta": "the algebraic sum of the primary forces must be equal to zero", "optb": "the algebraic sum of the couples about any point in the plane of the primary forces must be equal to zero", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The gear train usually employed in clocks is a", "opta": "simple gear train", "optb": "reverted gear train", "optc": "sun and planet gear", "optd": "differential gear", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A mass of 1 kg is attached to the end of a spring with a stiffness of 0.7 N/mm. The critical damping coefficient of this system is", "opta": "1.4 N-s/m", "optb": "18.52 N-s/m", "optc": "52.92 N-s/m", "optd": "529.2 N-s/m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cam follower generally used in automobile engines is", "opta": "knife edge follower", "optb": "fiat faced follower", "optc": "spherical faced follower", "optd": "roller follower", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All the commercial liquid fuels are derived from natural petroleum (or crude oil).", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cycle consisting of one constant pressure, one constant volume and two isentropic processes is known as", "opta": "Carnot cycle", "optb": "Stirling cycle", "optc": "Otto cycle", "optd": "Diesel cycle", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency and work ratio of a simple gas turbine cycle are", "opta": "low", "optb": "very low", "optc": "high", "optd": "very high", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of heat required to raise the temperature of the unit mass of gas through one degree at constant volume, is called", "opta": "specific heat at constant volume", "optb": "specific heat at constant pressure", "optc": "kilo Joule", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is a loss of heat in an irreversible process.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An adiabatic process is one in which", "opta": "no heat enters or leaves the gas", "optb": "the temperature of the gas changes", "optc": "the change in internal energy is equal to the mechanical workdone", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water gas is obtained by passing air and a large amount of steam over waste coal at about 650\u00b0C.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following represents Otto cycle on temperature - entropy (T - s) diagram?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the gas is heated at constant volume, the heat supplied increases the internal energy of the gas.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the lightest and most volatile liquid fuel?", "opta": "Gasoline", "optb": "Kerosene", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The processes occuring in open system which permit the transfer of mass to and from the system, are known as", "opta": "flow processes", "optb": "non-flow processes", "optc": "adiabatic processes", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the minimum atomic mass?", "opta": "Oxygen", "optb": "Sulphur", "optc": "Nitrogen", "optd": "Carbon", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Workdone in a free expansion process is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "minimum", "optc": "maximum", "optd": "positive", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pressure exerted by an ideal gas is __________ of the kinetic energy of all the molecules contained in a unit volume of gas.", "opta": "one-half", "optb": "one-third", "optc": "two-third", "optd": "three-fourth", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The compression ratio for petrol engines is", "opta": "3 to 6", "optb": "5 to 8", "optc": "15 to 20", "optd": "20 to 30", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most probable velocity of the gas molecules is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of Diesel cycle approaches to Otto cycle efficiency when", "opta": "cut-off is increased", "optb": "cut-off is decreased", "optc": "cut-off is zero", "optd": "cut-off is constant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The entropy __________ in an irreversible cyclic process.", "opta": "remains constant", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The atomic mass of oxygen is", "opta": "12", "optb": "14", "optc": "16", "optd": "32", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of specific heat at constant pressure (cp) and specific heat at constant volume (cv) is", "opta": "equal to one", "optb": "less than one", "optc": "greater than one", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Carbonisation of coal consists of", "opta": "drying and crushing the coal to a fine powder", "optb": "moulding the finely ground coal under pressure with or without a binding material", "optc": "heating the wood with a limited supply of air to temperature not less than 280\u00b0C", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of Stirling cycle is __________ Carnot cycle.", "opta": "greater than", "optb": "less than", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Gay-Lussac law for a perfect gas, p/T = constant, if v is kept constant.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is no change in internal energy in an isothermal process.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the value of n = 0 in the equation pvn = C, then the process is called", "opta": "constant volume process", "optb": "adiabatic process", "optc": "constant pressure process", "optd": "isothermal process", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of specific heat at constant pressure (cp) is __________ that of at constant volume (cv).", "opta": "less than", "optb": "equal to", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When coal is strongly heated continuously for 42 to 48 hours in the absence of air in a closed vessel, the process is known as __________ of fuel.", "opta": "atomisation", "optb": "carbonisation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is correct?", "opta": "Absolute pressure = Gauge pressure + Atmospheric pressure", "optb": "Gauge pressure = Absolute pressure + Atmospheric pressure", "optc": "Atmospheric pressure = Absolute pressure + Gauge pressure", "optd": "Absolute pressure = Gauge pressure - Atmospheric pressure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distillation carried out in such a way that the liquid with the lowest boiling point is first evaporated and recondensed, then the liquid with the next higher boiling point is then evaporated and recondensed, and so on until all the available liquid fuels are separately recovered in the sequence of their boiling points. Such a process is called", "opta": "cracking", "optb": "carbonisation", "optc": "fractional distillation", "optd": "full distillation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect?", "opta": "The liquid fuels consist of hydrocarbons.", "optb": "The liquid fuels have higher calorific value than solid fuels.", "optc": "The solid fuels have higher calorific value than liquid fuels.", "optd": "A good fuel should have low ignition point.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following gas is mostly used in town for street and domestic lighting and heating?", "opta": "Producer gas", "optb": "Coal gas", "optc": "Mond gas", "optd": "Coke oven gas", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of gas constant (R) in S. I. units is", "opta": "0.287 J/kgK", "optb": "2.87 J/kgK", "optc": "28.7 J/kgK", "optd": "287 J/kgK", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the first law of thermodynamics, the total energy of the system remains constant.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of Diesel cycle increases with", "opta": "decrease in cut-off", "optb": "increase in cut-off", "optc": "constant cut-off", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coal gas is obtained by mixing coal and gas at ambient conditions.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Avogadro's law, the density of any two gases is __________ their molecular masses, if the gases are at the same temperature and pressure.", "opta": "equal to", "optb": "directly proportional to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The kinetic energy of molecules of a gas becomes zero at absolute zero temperature.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One kg of carbon monoxide requires __________ kg of oxygen to produce 11/7 kg of carbon dioxide gas.", "opta": "All", "optb": "4/7", "optc": "11/4", "optd": "9/7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The absolute zero temperature is taken as", "opta": "-273\u00b0C", "optb": "273\u00b0C", "optc": "237\u00b0F", "optd": "-237\u00b0F", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific heat of water is", "opta": "1.817", "optb": "2512", "optc": "4.187", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The constant pressure, constant volume and constant pvn processes are regarded as irreversible process.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stirling and Ericsson cycles are", "opta": "reversible cycles", "optb": "irreversible cycles", "optc": "semi-reversible cycles", "optd": "quasi-static cycles", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When cut-off ratio is __________ the efficiency of Diesel cycle approaches to Otto cycle efficiency.", "opta": "zero", "optb": "1/5", "optc": "4/5", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A series of operations, which takes place in a certain order and restore the initial conditions at the end, is known as", "opta": "reversible cycle", "optb": "irreversible cycle", "optc": "thermodynamic cycle", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An isothermal process is governed by", "opta": "Boyle's law", "optb": "Charles' law", "optc": "Gay-Lussac law", "optd": "Avogadro's law", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sum of internal energy (U) and the product of pressure and volume (p.v) is known as", "opta": "workdone", "optb": "entropy", "optc": "enthalpy", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of 1 mm of Hg is equal to", "opta": "1.333 N/m2", "optb": "13.33 N/m2", "optc": "133.3 N/m2", "optd": "1333 N/m2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One kg of carbon requires 4/3 kg of oxygen and produces __________ kg of carbon monoxide gas.", "opta": "8/3", "optb": "11/3", "optc": "11/7", "optd": "7/3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The behaviour of a perfect gas, undergoing any change in the variables which control physical properties, is governed by", "opta": "Boyle's law", "optb": "Charles' law", "optc": "Gay-Lussac law", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The universal gas constant of a gas is the product of molecular mass of the gas and the gas constant.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Surface plate is used to check the trueness of flat surfaces.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A zinc diffusion process is called", "opta": "galvanising", "optb": "anodising", "optc": "parkerising", "optd": "sherardizing", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The accuracy of micrometers, calipers, dial indicators can be checked by a", "opta": "feeler gauge", "optb": "slip gauge", "optc": "ring gauge", "optd": "plug gauge", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of file used for a wood work is", "opta": "single-cut file", "optb": "double cut file", "optc": "rasp-cut file", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A taper provided on the pattern for its easy and clean withdrawl from the mould is known as", "opta": "machining allowance", "optb": "draft allowance", "optc": "shrinkage allowance", "optd": "distortion allowance", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In arc welding, the electric arc is produced between the work and the electrode by", "opta": "voltage", "optb": "flow of current", "optc": "contact resistance", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a centrifugal casting method", "opta": "core is made of sand", "optb": "core is made of ferrous metal", "optc": "core is made of non-ferrous metal", "optd": "no core is used", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The draft or taper allowance on casting is generally", "opta": "1 to 2 mm/m", "optb": "2 to 5 mm/m", "optc": "5 to 10 mm/m", "optd": "10 to 15 mm/m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following welding process uses non-consumable electrodes?", "opta": "TIG welding", "optb": "MIG welding", "optc": "Manual arc welding", "optd": "Submerged arc welding", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a bilateral system of tolerance, the tolerance is allowed on", "opta": "one side of the actual size", "optb": "one side of the nominal size", "optc": "both sides of the actual size", "optd": "both sides of the nominal size", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a hot chamber die casting machine", "opta": "ferrous alloys with low melting temperature are casted", "optb": "ferrous alloys with high melting temperature are casted", "optc": "non-ferrous alloys with low melting temperature are casted", "optd": "non-ferrous alloys with high melting temperature are casted", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chisel used for cutting key ways is", "opta": "flat chisel", "optb": "cape chisel", "optc": "round nose chisel", "optd": "diamond pointed chisel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature at which the new grains are formed in the metal is called", "opta": "lower critical temperature", "optb": "upper critical temperature", "optc": "eutectic temperature", "optd": "recrystallisation temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thread rolling is restricted to", "opta": "ferrous materials", "optb": "ductile materials", "optc": "hard materials", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In sheet metal blanking, shear is provided on punches and dies so that", "opta": "press load is reduced", "optb": "good cut edge is obtained", "optc": "warping of sheet is minimised", "optd": "cut blanks are straight", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In welding copper alloys with TIG arc welding", "opta": "direct current with straight polarity is used", "optb": "direct current with reversed polarity is used", "optc": "alternating current is used", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The algebraic difference between the minimum limit and the basic size is called", "opta": "actual deviation", "optb": "upper deviation", "optc": "lower deviation", "optd": "fundamental deviation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature of oxy-hydrogen flame is __________ oxy-acetylene flame.", "opta": "same as", "optb": "less than", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following methods can be used for manufacturing 2 metre long seamless metallic tubes?", "opta": "Drawing", "optb": "Extrusion", "optc": "Rolling", "optd": "Extrusion and rolling", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A saw which cuts wood during the return stroke of the saw is known as", "opta": "push saw", "optb": "pull saw or draw saw", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The low pressure acetylene is produced at the welding site by the chemical reaction between water and calcium carbonate.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fullers are used", "opta": "for finishing flat surfaces", "optb": "for necking down a piece of work", "optc": "for punching a hole", "optd": "to finish the punched hole", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cold chisels are made by", "opta": "drawing", "optb": "rolling", "optc": "piercing", "optd": "forging", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The property of sand due to which it evolves a great amount of steam and other gases is called", "opta": "collapsibility", "optb": "permeability", "optc": "cohesiveness", "optd": "adhesiveness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The centrifugal casting method, is used for casting articles of", "opta": "symmetrical shape about vertical axis", "optb": "symmetrical shape about horizontal axis", "optc": "irregular shape", "optd": "non-ferrous metal only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Metal patterns are used for", "opta": "small castings", "optb": "large castings", "optc": "complicated castings", "optd": "large scale production of castings", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The instrument which has all the features of try-square, bevel protractor, rule and scriber, is", "opta": "outside micrometer", "optb": "inside micrometer", "optc": "depth gauge micrometer", "optd": "combination set", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a hole or cavity to be cored is not in line with the parting surface, then a __________ is used.", "opta": "horizontal core", "optb": "vertical core", "optc": "drop core", "optd": "balanced core", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bloom is smaller than a billet.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In average work, the tolerance produced by investment casting method is", "opta": "\u00b10.05 mm", "optb": "+0.2 mm", "optc": "+05 mm", "optd": "+1 mm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of a riser is to", "opta": "deliver molten metal into the mould cavity", "optb": "act as a reservoir for the molten metal", "optc": "feed the molten metal to the casting in order to compensate for the shrinkage", "optd": "deliver the molten metal from pouring basin to gate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The blank diameter used in thread rolling will be", "opta": "equal to minor diameter of the thread", "optb": "equal to pitch diameter of the thread", "optc": "a little larger than the minor diameter of the thread", "optd": "a little larger than the pitch diameter of the thread", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cross-section of a chisel is usually", "opta": "rectangular", "optb": "square", "optc": "hexagonal", "optd": "octagonal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A plug gauge is used to check the diameter of shafts and studs.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In back-hand welding, the angle between the welding torch and the work is kept as", "opta": "30\u00b0-40\u00b0", "optb": "40\u00b0-50\u00b0", "optc": "50\u00b0-60\u00b0", "optd": "60\u00b0-70\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The machining allowance provided on patterns depends upon", "opta": "type of casting metal", "optb": "size and shape of casting", "optc": "method of casting used", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In submerged arc welding, an arc is produced between a", "opta": "carbon electrode and the work", "optb": "metal electrode and the work", "optc": "bare metal electrode and the work", "optd": "two tungsten electrodes and the work", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In shielded arc welding", "opta": "large electrode is used", "optb": "welding rod coated with slag is used", "optc": "welding rod coated with fluxing material is used", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a die casting method, the molten metal is forced into mould under high pressure.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a centrifugal casting method, the impurities are collected in the centre of the casting.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a hot chamber die casting machine", "opta": "melting pot is separate from the machine", "optb": "melting pot is an integral part of the machine", "optc": "melting pot may have any location", "optd": "high temperature and pressure is used", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The electrodes used in spot welding have a tip of", "opta": "stainless steel", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "copper", "optd": "brass", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Blanking and piercing operations can be performed simultaneously in a", "opta": "simple die", "optb": "progressive die", "optc": "compound die", "optd": "combination die", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pattern maker's shrinkage rule considers", "opta": "all pattern allowances", "optb": "only shrinkage allowance", "optc": "all materials to be cast", "optd": "all materials of the pattern", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tolerance produced by shell moulding process of casting is", "opta": "+0.05 mm", "optb": "\u00b10.2 mm", "optc": "+0.5 mm", "optd": "\u00b11 mm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Galvanising is a", "opta": "zinc diffusion process", "optb": "process of coating zinc by hot dipping", "optc": "process used for making thin phosphate coating on steel", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ferrous metals require more machining allowance than non-ferrous metals.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a four high rolling mill, there are four rolls out of which", "opta": "one is working roll and three are backing up rolls", "optb": "two are working rolls and two are backing up rolls", "optc": "three are working rolls and one is backing up roll", "optd": "all of the four are working rolls", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a pattern is made in three parts, the bottom part is known as a cope.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In __________ welding, the weld may be made either from left to right or from right to left.", "opta": "fore-hand", "optb": "back-hand", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a conical-shaped recess around a hole, often used to receive a tapered screw head:", "opta": "Boss", "optb": "Spotface", "optc": "Counterbore", "optd": "Countersink", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is an angled surface used on cylinders to make them easier to handle:", "opta": "Fillet", "optb": "Taper", "optc": "Chamfer", "optd": "Lug", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are used to attach parts to a cylinder so they won't turn on it:", "opta": "Lugs and bearings", "optb": "Keyseats and bearings", "optc": "Knurls and keys", "optd": "Keys and keyways/keyseats", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a flat or rounded tab protruding from a surface, usually to provide a method for attachment:", "opta": "Lug", "optb": "Boss", "optc": "Chamfer", "optd": "Spotface", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a hollow cylinder that is often used as a protective sleeve or guide or as a bearing:", "opta": "Lug", "optb": "Bushing", "optc": "Chamfer", "optd": "Knurl", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a rounded exterior blend between surfaces:", "opta": "Fillet", "optb": "Round", "optc": "Taper", "optd": "Chamfer", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Press-Pull tool will ________ the face of a solid model in the direction it faces.", "opta": "taper", "optb": "extrude", "optc": "spiral", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The View toolbar will position the view of the 3-D solid toward the ________.", "opta": "front", "optb": "left side", "optc": "SE isometric", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Free Orbit tool is found on the ____ toolbar.", "opta": "rotate", "optb": "move", "optc": "modify", "optd": "3-D Move", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The default position of the UCS icon is positioned at ________ on the AutoCAD grid.", "opta": "0,0,0", "optb": "10,10,10", "optc": "20,20,20", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cylinder can be created by drawing a rectangular shape then the ________ tool.", "opta": "Revolve", "optb": "Sweep", "optc": "Extrude", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The MASSPROP shortcut will provide the following information.", "opta": "mass", "optb": "volume", "optc": "bounding box", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The 3-D commands on the Modeling toolbar include ________.", "opta": "box", "optb": "sphere", "optc": "extrude", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CAD programs which incorporate parametric modeling utilize a system in which the dimensions control the ________.", "opta": "size and shape of the model features", "optb": "perspective of the model", "optc": "shading used to render the model", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to create one solid model from two or more separate solid shapes the drafter will need to position them and then ________.", "opta": "use Union to join them", "optb": "use the Join command", "optc": "use the Add Parts tool", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Conceptual Visual Style tool is located on the ________ toolbar.", "opta": "Visual Styles", "optb": "Modify", "optc": "3-D Modeling", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The building construction industry relies on sets of ________ drawings to construct homes and commercial buildings.", "opta": "mechanical", "optb": "isometric", "optc": "architectural working", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The text height for room names should be set to ________for a drawing that will be plotted to a scale of \u00bc\" = 1'-0\".", "opta": "4\"", "optb": "5\"", "optc": "6\"", "optd": "8\"", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The architectural drafter usually begins a set of working drawings by creating the ________ plan first.", "opta": "foundation", "optb": "floor plan", "optc": "elevations", "optd": "building section", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Once the architect has finalized the house plans with the client any changes to the design requested by the client will require a ________.", "opta": "change order", "optb": "modification slip", "optc": "whole new set of drawings", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The foundation contractor will work with the following architectural plans.", "opta": "foundation", "optb": "site plan", "optc": "floor plan", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To insure that everyone understands what the electrical symbols represent it is customary to include a ____ on the electrical sheet.", "opta": "list", "optb": "part number", "optc": "electrical legend", "optd": "electrical layer", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On a floor plan the dashed line that appears approximately 24\" outside the exterior wall represents the ________.", "opta": "sidewalk", "optb": "roof overhang", "optc": "plumbing drain lines", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The site plan illustrates ________.", "opta": "the floor plan", "optb": "where the house sits on the property", "optc": "the roof plan", "optd": "where the garage and driveway are located", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Generally, the units used on an architectural drawing are set to ________.", "opta": "Architectural", "optb": "engineering", "optc": "metric", "optd": "civil", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Elevation drawings will include information about ________.", "opta": "roof pitch", "optb": "siding", "optc": "window style", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lines used to create the auxiliary view should appear as ________ in the finished view.", "opta": "Object lines", "optb": "Construction lines", "optc": "Reference lines", "optd": "Construction lines", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The offset distance for the width (front to back) distance of the auxiliary view is the same distance of the ________ in the top view.", "opta": "Width", "optb": "height", "optc": "length", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The principle reason for using an auxiliary view is ________.", "opta": "to eliminate hidden lines", "optb": "to create a true projection plane from an inclined plane in one of the primary views", "optc": "to show cylinders as ellipses", "optd": "to locate center marks", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Circular shapes appear in this fashion when viewed at an angle other than 90 degrees:", "opta": "Circular", "optb": "Elliptical", "optc": "Lengthened", "optd": "Angular", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When adding dimensions to an auxiliary view it will be necessary to use the ________ tool.", "opta": "Linear dimension", "optb": "Aligned dimension", "optc": "Baseline dimension", "optd": "Angle dimension", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An efficient method for trimming the corners on an auxiliary view is to use the ________.", "opta": "0 radius fillet", "optb": "Hatch tool", "optc": "Extend tool", "optd": "Grips function", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of auxiliary view, a break line is used to indicate the imaginary break in the views:", "opta": "Primary", "optb": "Secondary", "optc": "Revolved", "optd": "Partial", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When using the descriptive geometry method to create an auxiliary view the drafter should ________.", "opta": "rotate the snap grid to the same angle of the inclined plane", "optb": "offset the right vertical line of the front view", "optc": "rotate the top line of the front view 45 degrees", "optd": "offset the top line of the front view 2 inches", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the most common application for developments and intersections:", "opta": "Sheet metal construction", "optb": "Piping", "optc": "Architecture", "optd": "Mechanical engineering", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of auxiliary view is projected onto a plane that is perpendicular to one of the principal planes of projection:", "opta": "Primary", "optb": "Secondary", "optc": "Revolved", "optd": "Successive", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A partial auxiliary view usually shows only features on the ________ of the inclined line and not any projection of other planes.", "opta": "hidden lines", "optb": "plane", "optc": "center lines", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A partial auxiliary view is used to show only the ________ in the auxiliary view.", "opta": "projected inclined plane", "optb": "the projected top view", "optc": "the projected side view", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of surface may be a plane, a single curved surface, or a warped surface:", "opta": "Edge surface", "optb": "Ruled surface", "optc": "Auxiliary surface", "optd": "Developed surface", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of view, the cutting plane line indicates both the location of the cutting plane and the direction of sight:", "opta": "Removed section", "optb": "Revolved section", "optc": "Auxiliary section", "optd": "Partial section", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The principle views associated with orthographic projection are ________.", "opta": "Front view", "optb": "Right side view", "optc": "Top view", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A secondary auxiliary view is a projection off of the ________.", "opta": "Front view", "optb": "Top view", "optc": "Primary auxiliary view", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of solid is formed by sweeping a shape along a linear path:", "opta": "Planar solid", "optb": "Revolved solid", "optc": "Warped solid", "optd": "Extruded solid", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In isometric projection, all distances are approximately this percentage of their true size:", "opta": "120 percent", "optb": "80 percent", "optc": "50 percent", "optd": "20 percent", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Angles project true size only when the plane containing the angle and plane of projection are this:", "opta": "Adjacent", "optb": "Aligned", "optc": "Perpendicular", "optd": "Parallel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of projection, each of the axes has different ratios of foreshortening:", "opta": "Isometric", "optb": "Dimetric", "optc": "Trimetric", "optd": "Parallel", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lines of an isometric drawing that are not parallel to the isometric axes are called this:", "opta": "Trimetric lines", "optb": "Nonisometric lines", "optc": "Multiview lines", "optd": "Dimetric lines", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of axonometric drawing has equal foreshortening along two axis directions and a different amount on the third axis:", "opta": "Dimetric", "optb": "Multiview", "optc": "Isometric", "optd": "Trimetric", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The edges of a cube in isometric projection make angles of this many degrees with each other:", "opta": "30", "optb": "60", "optc": "90", "optd": "120", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An AutoCAD term that refers to a pre-drawn object which is stored in a drawing file and can be inserted into any other drawing file as needed is a ________.", "opta": "Block", "optb": "brick", "optc": "balloon", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most architectural firms and mechanical design companies utilize different categories of blocks. These sets of blocks are usually housed in ________.", "opta": "block vaults", "optb": "block libraries", "optc": "block books", "optd": "block references", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In some circumstances an entire drawing can be inserted into a different drawing as a block. When this is used the base point will default to ________.", "opta": "0,0", "optb": "10,10", "optc": "20,20", "optd": "30,30", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When creating your own blocks it is important to avoid drawing any portion of the block in the ________ layer.", "opta": "0", "optb": "center line", "optc": "hatch", "optd": "hidden line", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Newer versions of AutoCAD utilize the ________ to make block library management very easy.", "opta": "File / find", "optb": "Design Center", "optc": "File / search", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the drafter types the word BLOCK or selects the Make Block tool from the Draw tool bar the ________ will appear.", "opta": "grid", "optb": "Block Text Box", "optc": "Block Definition Dialog", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When creating a block the drafter needs to pay particular attention to selecting a base point because it determines the ________.", "opta": "scale", "optb": "rotation angle", "optc": "insertion point", "optd": "color", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When using versions of AutoCAD prior to Release 2006 it may be necessary to ________ a block in order to edit it.", "opta": "copy", "optb": "explode", "optc": "offset", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some common blocks used by architectural drafters include ________.", "opta": "door swings", "optb": "ceiling fans", "optc": "appliances", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inserting blocks into a drawing file usually requires exacting placement. The drafter should insure that ________ is turned on.", "opta": "O Snaps", "optb": "Ortho", "optc": "Grid", "optd": "Dynamic Input", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Using the Relative Polar Coordinate System to add a 3 inch line that is 45 degrees from the end point of the line created above the drafter would ________.", "opta": "type @3<45 and enter", "optb": "type 3 back slash and enter", "optc": "type 3 forward slash and enter", "optd": "type 3 and try to use the Dynamic Input readout to find the end point", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A line with a tapering width can be easily created by using the ________ tool.", "opta": "circle", "optb": "eclipse", "optc": "line", "optd": "polyline", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Understanding the Cartesian coordinate system will help the beginning drafter ________.", "opta": "control the accuracy of the drawing", "optb": "produce a visible grid system", "optc": "select a different text style", "optd": "choose various line types", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The UCS icon represents the intersection of the ________.", "opta": "X axis", "optb": "Y axis", "optc": "Z axis", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When using the direct entry method to create a horizontal line exactly three inches long the drafter should ________ first.", "opta": "pull the line from away from the starting point very carefully", "optb": "insure that Ortho is on", "optc": "enter 3 for the length of the line", "optd": "read the coordinate position on the Dynamic Readout", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to set drawing limits for a \"C\" size architectural drawing the drafter should set the limits to ________.", "opta": "0,0 and 2,9", "optb": "0,0 and 17,11", "optc": "0,0 and 18,24", "optd": "0,0 and 34,24", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One quick way to view the entire drawing area is to use the Zoom command by typing ________.", "opta": "type Z enter A enter", "optb": "type Z enter E enter", "optc": "type SHOWALL enter", "optd": "type ALL enter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When setting up a mechanical drawing in AutoCAD the drafter should set the units to ________.", "opta": "fractional", "optb": "decimal", "optc": "architectural", "optd": "metric", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When drawing a line using the relative coordinate system a line is created from ________.", "opta": "0,0", "optb": "the ending point of the last line", "optc": "the beginning point of the last line", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you use the absolute coordinate system to create a line from a starting point of 0, 0 8 units on the X axis and 5 units on the Y axis you enter ________ for the second point.", "opta": "8,5", "optb": "5,8", "optc": "0,8", "optd": "5,0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The condition of a part when it contains the least amount of material is referred to as ________.", "opta": "smallest", "optb": "LMC", "optc": "MMC", "optd": "actual size", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is used to indicate that a surface is to be machined:", "opta": "Finish mark", "optb": "Machining mark", "optc": "Roughness indicator", "optd": "Coordinate mark", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ________ tool on the Dimension tool bar places the length of an arch on a drawing.", "opta": "Arc Radius", "optb": "Arc Length", "optc": "Radius", "optd": "Diameter", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "How can the drafter prevent AutoCAD from placing or stacking another center mark on a circle when adding a diameter dimension to it?", "opta": "Explode the dimension and then erase the center mark.", "optb": "Use the Properties dialog box to turn off the center mark of the dimension.", "optc": "It can't be done.", "optd": "Use the trim tool to take away the stacked center mark.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of dimensioning, allowance must be made for bends:", "opta": "Angular", "optb": "Tolerance", "optc": "Datum", "optd": "Sheet metal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One way to evenly space dimensions on a drawing is to use the ________.", "opta": "Dimension Space tool", "optb": "Linear tool", "optc": "Continue tool", "optd": "Baseline tool", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ________ tool on the Dimension tool bar will place several dimensions at one time by using a selection box placed over several part features.", "opta": "Linear", "optb": "Continue", "optc": "Baseline", "optd": "Quick Dimension", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A circular arc is dimensioned in the view where you see its true shape by giving the value for its:", "opta": "Diameter", "optb": "Arc length", "optc": "Radius", "optd": "Chord length", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the total amount that the feature on the actual part is allowed to vary from what is specified by the dimension:", "opta": "Allowance", "optb": "Tolerance", "optc": "Specification", "optd": "Difference", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ________ dimension tool will place the length of an angled line.", "opta": "Aligned", "optb": "Angle", "optc": "Linear", "optd": "Radial", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Placement of dimensions on a drawing is controlled by ________.", "opta": "ANSI", "optb": "The design engineer", "optc": "Corporate drafting standards", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Baseline dimensions are referenced from a common geometric feature known as a ________.", "opta": "edge", "optb": "corner", "optc": "datum", "optd": "point of reference", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Given a situation in which the drafter has crossed extension lines in a drawing what can be done to clean up the point of crossing?", "opta": "Use the Modify tool to clean up the extension lines.", "optb": "Use the Tolerance tool to clean up the extension lines.", "optc": "Use the Break tool to clean up the extension lines.", "optd": "Use the stretch tool to clean up the extension lines.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a thin solid line directing attention to a note or dimension and starting with an arrowhead or dot:", "opta": "Dimension line", "optb": "Extension line", "optc": "Leader", "optd": "Specification", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum and minimum sizes of a feature are identified by a ________ tolerance.", "opta": "Limits", "optb": "GD&T;", "optc": "reference", "optd": "allowance", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a line terminated by arrowheads, indicating the direction and extent of a dimension:", "opta": "Dimension line", "optb": "Extension line", "optc": "Arrowhead line", "optd": "Centerline", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In U.S. structural and architectural drafting, all dimensions of this length are usually expressed in feet and inches:", "opta": "One inch or over", "optb": "One foot or over", "optc": "One yard or over", "optd": "One rod or over", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Architectural dimensioning standards allow for the placement of dimensions inside the floor plan. These inside dimensions locate interior ________.", "opta": "door openings and walls", "optb": "centers of cabinets", "optc": "windows", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When dimensioning architectural drawings architects will utilize both ________ and ________ options.", "opta": "Baseline and continuous", "optb": "Baseline and linear", "optc": "Quick dim and linear", "optd": "Linear and continuous", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Architectural dimensioning is usually done in ________.", "opta": "Even numbers", "optb": "Feet and inches", "optc": "Feet only", "optd": "Inches only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some of the standard AutoCAD text styles used in architectural drawings includes ________.", "opta": "CityBlueprint", "optb": "CountryBlueprint", "optc": "Stylus BT", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimension text is generally placed above the ________ line.", "opta": "Dimension", "optb": "extension", "optc": "center", "optd": "leader", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The architectural and construction industries use the United States National CAD standard (NCS) system on many ________ projects.", "opta": "residential", "optb": "commercial", "optc": "aerospace", "optd": "publicly funded", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There should be a visible gap between the wall and the ________ line.", "opta": "dimension", "optb": "extension", "optc": "center", "optd": "leader", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimensions are used on the elevation plan to describe ________.", "opta": "Finished floor elevations", "optb": "Roof overhangs", "optc": "Roof pitch angles", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The second line of dimensions out from the plan generally includes ________.", "opta": "Centers of doors and windows", "optb": "The distances between outside walls and interior walls.", "optc": "The measurement from the outside of the brick to the inside of the exterior wall.", "optd": "The measurement from one outside corner to the opposite outside corner.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dimension text size is determined by what the architect deems necessary in ________.", "opta": "Model space", "optb": "Paper space", "optc": "The Finished plot", "optd": "The PDF file", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Using this as a communication and design review tool can help shorten the process and eliminate productivity barriers:", "opta": "Development plans", "optb": "Portable document files", "optc": "The Internet and e-mail", "optd": "Gantt charts", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If designs require changes, they should be documented with:", "opta": "Development plans", "optb": "Product proposals", "optc": "Document reviews", "optd": "Engineering change orders", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Once a drawing is determined to be complete, the title block is used to document the change from:", "opta": "A draft to a finished drawing", "optb": "A finished to a working drawing", "optc": "An assembly to a finished drawing", "optd": "A working drawing to a draft", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Drawings created with commercial software are typically saved as:", "opta": "Rapid prototypes", "optb": "Electronic files", "optc": "Draft drawings", "optd": "Change orders", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On typical electronic diagrams, these items need not be shown unless they are needed for clarification:", "opta": "Transmission diagrams", "optb": "Operating relays", "optc": "Closed relays", "optd": "Terminal circles", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Schematic and single-line diagrams should be arranged so that signal or transmission path from input to output proceeds in this fashion:", "opta": "Right to left and top to bottom", "optb": "Right to left and bottom to top", "optc": "Left to right and top to bottom", "optd": "Left to right and bottom to top", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Switches and relays should be shown in this position with no operating force or applied energy:", "opta": "Normal", "optb": "Closed", "optc": "Offset", "optd": "Application", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These items typically are not used in new designs, but are still common in high-power amplifiers:", "opta": "Amplifier tubes", "optb": "Electron tubes", "optc": "Signal relays", "optd": "Switches", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of circuit is a semiconductor wafer or chip:", "opta": "Integrated circuit", "optb": "Transmission circuit", "optc": "Plotted circuit", "optd": "Conducted circuit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spur gear design normally begins with selecting this:", "opta": "Rack size", "optb": "Tooth size", "optc": "Gear size", "optd": "Pitch diameter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most common geometric form used in gears today is this:", "opta": "Involute profile", "optb": "Convolute profie", "optc": "Base circle", "optd": "Spur circle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a curve showing the displacement of the follower as ordinates on a base line that represents one revolution of the cam:", "opta": "Displacement diagram", "optb": "Follower", "optc": "Cam cycle", "optd": "Reciprocation chart", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gear teeth formed on a flat surface are called this:", "opta": "Pinion", "optb": "Rack", "optc": "Spur", "optd": "Teeth", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These gears transmit power between shafts whose axes intersect at any angle:", "opta": "Worm gears", "optb": "Spur gears", "optc": "Bevel gears", "optd": "Racks", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EDM is the acronym for:", "opta": "Enterprise data management", "optb": "Engineering drawing management", "optc": "Enterprise drawing manipulation", "optd": "Engineering data manipulation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Technical drawings typically serve one of three purposes:", "opta": "Visualization, Communication, or Documentation", "optb": "Visualization, Dimensioning, or Documentation", "optc": "Communication, Documentation, or Installation", "optd": "Documentation, Installation, or Engineering", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The organized and orderly approach to solving problems is known as the:", "opta": "Engineering process", "optb": "Design process", "optc": "Aesthetic process", "optd": "Functional process", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the range of digital or hard copy documents that specify the physical function requirements for a product:", "opta": "Product design", "optb": "Product definition", "optc": "Drawing definition", "optd": "Engineering design", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PDM is the acronym for:", "opta": "Project drawing management", "optb": "Product drawing manipulation", "optc": "Product data management", "optd": "Project data manipulation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a systematic approach that integrates the design and manufacture of products with the goal of optimizing the process:", "opta": "Traditional engineering design", "optb": "The manufacturing process", "optc": "Concurrent design", "optd": "Design for recycling", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Isometric drawings are often used by ________ to help illustrate complex designs.", "opta": "mechanical engineers", "optb": "piping drafters", "optc": "aerospace engineers", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to create an isometric circle to represent a hole through the top surface of a box, the drafter must insure that the correct isoplane has been selected by scrolling through the isoplanes using the ________ key.", "opta": "F1", "optb": "F3", "optc": "F5", "optd": "F8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fillet is a rounded surface on the ________ corner of a part.", "opta": "Inside", "optb": "outside", "optc": "radial", "optd": "isoplane", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Before starting an isometric drawing in AutoCAD the drafter needs to ________.", "opta": "set the grid to isometric", "optb": "set the current layer to Defpoints", "optc": "turn Object Snap off", "optd": "turn Ortho off", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A round is a rounded surface on the ________ corner of a part.", "opta": "inside", "optb": "outside", "optc": "radial", "optd": "isoplane", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Architectural drafters generally prefer to use ________ drawings to help illustrate 3-dimensional views of a structure.", "opta": "isometric", "optb": "perspective", "optc": "orthographic", "optd": "auxiliary", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The bounding box method for setting up an isometric drawing helps the drafter ________.", "opta": "confine the isometric drawing to its maximum size", "optb": "figure what lines are to be illustrated vertical and horizontal", "optc": "position the isometric drawing in paper space", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Offset tool should only be used for placing ________ in an isometric drawing.", "opta": "circles", "optb": "horizontal lines", "optc": "vertical lines", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When creating an isometric drawing in AutoCAD the drafter can utilize the Dynamic Input and Polar Coordinate system to place both vertical and horizontal lines. A line created from one point 3 inches at 180 degrees would be a ________ line.", "opta": "horizontal", "optb": "vertical", "optc": "inclined", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AutoCAD refers to isometric ellipses as ________.", "opta": "Ellipses", "optb": "isoellipses", "optc": "isocircles", "optd": "circles", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These maps are used in planning installations of trees, shrubbery, drives, and other garden features:", "opta": "Landscape maps", "optb": "Engineering maps", "optc": "Topographic maps", "optd": "Cadastral maps", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are special installations of stone or concrete marking the locations of points accurately determined by precise surveying:", "opta": "Topographic marks", "optb": "Hatchures", "optc": "Monuments", "optd": "Pillars", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are vertical distances above a common datum, reference plane, or point:", "opta": "Plats", "optb": "Elevations", "optc": "Traverse", "optd": "Profiles", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are lines drawn on a map to locate, in the plan view, points of equal ground elevation:", "opta": "Contours", "optb": "Elevations", "optc": "Profiles", "optd": "Hatchures", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These maps are used to plan construction projects that locate construction features so they fit the topography of the area:", "opta": "Subdivision plats", "optb": "Landscape maps", "optc": "Structural topography maps", "optd": "Structure location plans", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of drawing is created to calculate areas, locate property lines, and locate building projects and facilities:", "opta": "Traverse", "optb": "Contour", "optc": "City map", "optd": "Plat", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are accurately drawn maps of cities and towns showing property lines and other features that control property ownership:", "opta": "Monument maps", "optb": "Cadastral maps", "optc": "City maps", "optd": "Topographic maps", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When lettering a CAD drawing, for clarity you should limit the number of fonts to:", "opta": "One", "optb": "Two", "optc": "Three", "optd": "Any number", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The primary unit of measurement for engineering drawings and design in the mechanical industries is the:", "opta": "Millimeter", "optb": "Centimeter", "optc": "Meter", "optd": "Kilometer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These units are based on inch-foot and yard measurements:", "opta": "International customary units", "optb": "U.S. metric units", "optc": "U.S. customary units", "optd": "ISO international units", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is how axonometric, oblique, and perspective sketches show objects:", "opta": "Orthographically", "optb": "Pictorially", "optc": "Obliquely", "optd": "Parallel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of projection is when projectors are parallel to each other, but are at an angle other than 90 degrees to the plane of projection:", "opta": "Oblique projection", "optb": "Perpendicular projection", "optc": "Aesthetic projection", "optd": "Angular projection", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There are two main types of projection:", "opta": "Parallel and Orthographic", "optb": "Station-point and Perspective", "optc": "Parallel and Convergent", "optd": "Perspective and Parallel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This allows the designer to conceptualize objects more easily without having to make costly illustrations, models, or prototypes:", "opta": "Computer-aided manufacturing", "optb": "Computer-aided design", "optc": "Computer-aided engineering", "optd": "Computer-aided prototyping", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This allows the performance of structures to be analyzed and tested efficiently, accurately, and quickly:", "opta": "Computer-aided manufacturing", "optb": "Computer-aided design", "optc": "Computer-aided engineering", "optd": "Computer-aided prototyping", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of rapid prototyping system uses a laser to fuse powdered metals, plastics, or ceramics:", "opta": "Fused deposition modeling", "optb": "Stereolithography apparatus", "optc": "Solid ground curing", "optd": "Selective laser sintering", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This process recognizes the inherent interrelationships between design and manufacturing:", "opta": "Design for manufacture", "optb": "Design for manufacture and assembly", "optc": "Design for concurrent engineering", "optd": "Design for assembly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Manufacturing may produce these types of products:", "opta": "Discrete or continuous", "optb": "Raw material or parts", "optc": "Machinery or manufactured", "optd": "Processes or operations", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Approximately this much of the cost of product development and manufacture is determined at the design stage:", "opta": "40-50%", "optb": "60-75%", "optc": "70-80%", "optd": "75-85%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a solid shape that fits inside the mold and forms a hole in a cooled cast metal or molten plastic object:", "opta": "Core", "optb": "Cavity", "optc": "Prototype", "optd": "Hole mold", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The typical parts list should include the ________.", "opta": "part number", "optb": "manufacturing material", "optc": "number of parts needed", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A typical set of mechanical working drawings includes ________.", "opta": "exploded assembly", "optb": "part details", "optc": "parts list", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The title block used on working drawings should include the ________.", "opta": "sheet number", "optb": "line type", "optc": "layer set", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One critical issue drafters need to pay close attention to is the ________.", "opta": "size of the sheet", "optb": "designer's intent", "optc": "scale factor", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the mechanical design process the first step is to ________.", "opta": "brainstorm solutions", "optb": "prepare rough sketches", "optc": "prepare a budget", "optd": "identify the problem", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The text used on a typical detail sheet should be ________.", "opta": "placed horizontally", "optb": "in bold text", "optc": "in an architectural text style", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an exploded assembly drawing it is customary for the drafter to use a ________ line to illustrate how parts fit together.", "opta": "Phantom", "optb": "hidden", "optc": "dashed", "optd": "center", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is customary for the first sheet of a working drawing set to include ________.", "opta": "a parts list", "optb": "exploded assembly", "optc": "assembled assembly", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to create an accurate assembly drawing the drafter should create the ________ drawings first.", "opta": "Detail", "optb": "title block", "optc": "parts list", "optd": "isometric", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thread note for a typical bolt will include the ________.", "opta": "major diameter of the thread", "optb": "material", "optc": "center line", "optd": "offset distance", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a designer is developing a plan for a project in which the entire part is made out of \u00be\" thick plywood and he only wants to use one view, he should use the ________ view.", "opta": "front", "optb": "top", "optc": "right", "optd": "back", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In developing a multi-view drawing the drafter can use a ________ line to help locate the top and right side views.", "opta": "object", "optb": "hidden", "optc": "dimension", "optd": "miter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of line that projects from an object for the express purpose of locating a dimension is a ________ line.", "opta": "visible", "optb": "hidden", "optc": "extension", "optd": "dimension", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Center lines are used to locate or represent the centers of ________.", "opta": "arcs", "optb": "circles", "optc": "hidden round features", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Architectural drawings used to construct a house are often plotted with a scale of \u00bc\" = 1'-0\". What scale is this?", "opta": "Quarter", "optb": "Half", "optc": "Full", "optd": "Double", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In multi-view drawing it is common practice to include three views, the front, the top and the right side. If no dimensions are required on the right side view the drafter can ________.", "opta": "leave the view as is", "optb": "eliminate the view", "optc": "use the left view instead", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The AutoCAD command used to combine two or more primitive shapes into a single complex 3-dimensional model is ________.", "opta": "add", "optb": "union", "optc": "attach", "optd": "form", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most architectural drawings produced for field use by building contractors are printed on architectural \"D\" size paper which measures ________.", "opta": "24\" X 36\"", "optb": "18\" X 24\"", "optc": "11\" X 17\"", "optd": "34\" X 22\"", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Geometric primitives include shapes such as ________.", "opta": "boxes", "optb": "cylinders", "optc": "wedges", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A full scale technical drawing will have a scale factor of ________.", "opta": "1:1", "optb": "1:2", "optc": "2:1", "optd": "1:4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In oblique projection, important shapes should be in this position relative to the viewing plane:", "opta": "Parallel", "optb": "Perpendicular", "optc": "Adjacent", "optd": "Rotated", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a CAD system, you can draw an ellipse by specifying these:", "opta": "The bounding lines", "optb": "The midpoint and end points", "optc": "The center and major and minor axes", "optd": "The center and radius", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Oblique drawings are dimensioned in a similar fashion as these types of drawings:", "opta": "Orthographic", "optb": "Isometric", "optc": "Angular", "optd": "Parallel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an oblique drawing, equally spaced partial circles may be used to show this:", "opta": "Symbolic thread pitch", "optb": "Ellipses", "optc": "Cavalier drawings", "optd": "Projection points", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the receding lines are true length, and the projectors are at 45 degrees to the plane of projection, the oblique drawing is called this:", "opta": "Cabinet projection", "optb": "Cavalier projection", "optc": "Axonometric projection", "optd": "Isometric projection", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Oblique sections are useful to show this:", "opta": "Foreshortened features", "optb": "Oblique lines", "optc": "Interior shapes", "optd": "Projected features", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The top, front, and bottom views align in this manner:", "opta": "Horizontally", "optb": "Vertically", "optc": "According to the planar views", "optd": "Parallel to the frontal plane", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a plane is parallel to the plane of projection, it appears:", "opta": "True size", "optb": "As a line or edge", "optc": "Foreshortened", "optd": "As an oblique surface", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This line pattern is composed of three dashes, one long dash on each end with a short dash in the middle:", "opta": "Object", "optb": "Hidden", "optc": "Center", "optd": "Phantom", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the plane upon which the top view is projected:", "opta": "Horizontal", "optb": "Frontal", "optc": "Profile", "optd": "Base", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An advantage of this type of view is that each view shows the object all the way through as if it were transparent:", "opta": "Planar", "optb": "Horizontal", "optc": "Auxiliary", "optd": "Orthographic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of surface is tipped to all principal planes of projection and does not appear true size in any standard view:", "opta": "Foreshortened", "optb": "Parallel", "optc": "Orthographic", "optd": "Oblique", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two-point perspective is also known as:", "opta": "Two-view perspective", "optb": "Regular perspective", "optc": "Parallel perspective", "optd": "Angular perspective", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the intersection of the ground plane with the picture plane:", "opta": "Vanishing point", "optb": "Ground line", "optc": "Station point", "optd": "Horizon", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In perspective drawings this is placed between the observer and the object:", "opta": "Vanishing point / horizon", "optb": "Station point", "optc": "Ground line", "optd": "Plane of projection / picture plane", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When positioning this feature of perspective projection, the centerline of the cone of visual rays should be directed toward the approximate center of the object:", "opta": "Station point", "optb": "Vanishing point", "optc": "Horizon", "optd": "Ground line", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Perspective drawings are classified according to their number of these features:", "opta": "Station points", "optb": "Picture planes", "optc": "Vanishing points", "optd": "Ground lines", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of pipe is commonly used for water, steam, oil, and gas:", "opta": "Wrought iron or copper", "optb": "PVC or steel", "optc": "Steel or wrought iron", "optd": "Copper or PVC", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These types of pipes are generally connected with bell and spigot joints or flanged joints:", "opta": "Soil and waste", "optb": "Water and gas", "optc": "Water and steam", "optd": "Gas and soil", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When dimensioning piping drawings, you give the lengths of all runs of this type:", "opta": "Straight", "optb": "Angular", "optc": "Filleted", "optd": "Transverse", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of drawing, vertical pipes may be revolved into the horizontal plane:", "opta": "Standard view", "optb": "Elevation view", "optc": "Transverse piping", "optd": "Developed piping", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of drawing shows two lines representing the pipe diameter:", "opta": "Single-line", "optb": "Double-line", "optc": "Standard piping", "optd": "Centerline piping", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is used in applications for nonferrous construction:", "opta": "Copper tubing", "optb": "Steel pipe", "optc": "PVC pipe", "optd": "Iron tubing", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of pipe is commonly used for water or gas service, and also as soil pipe:", "opta": "PVC", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Steel", "optd": "Cast-iron", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of section is limited by a break line:", "opta": "Removed section", "optb": "Revolved section", "optc": "Broken-out section", "optd": "Half section", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Drafters should use a ________ in a section view of a mechanical part that includes the cylindrical view of a threaded hole.", "opta": "Center line", "optb": "Hatch line", "optc": "Poly line", "optd": "Dimension line", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The section view drawing in which one fourth of an object has been marked for removal is known as a ________ section.", "opta": "full", "optb": "half", "optc": "quarter", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In offset sections, offsets or bends in the cutting plane are all:", "opta": "90 degrees", "optb": "180 degrees", "optc": "Either 90 or 180 degrees", "optd": "30, 60, or 90 degrees", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When filling an area with a hatch pattern in AutoCAD the drafter needs to be able to ________.", "opta": "see the entire bounding area to hatch", "optb": "set Ortho on", "optc": "turn ISO grid off", "optd": "set the layer to Defpoints", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To avoid having to dimension to a hidden feature the drafter can utilize a ________ section.", "opta": "whole", "optb": "half", "optc": "broken out", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Objects that are symmetric can be shown effectively using this type of section:", "opta": "Quarter section", "optb": "Half section", "optc": "Full section", "optd": "Symmetric section", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of section is not in direct projection from the view containing the cutting plane:", "opta": "Revolved section", "optb": "Removed section", "optc": "Broken-out section", "optd": "Full section", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By using a ________ section of a cylindrical mechanical part the drafter should be able to show only one view of the part.", "opta": "half", "optb": "whole", "optc": "revolved", "optd": "broken out", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the section view, the areas that would have been in actual contact with the cutting plane are shown with:", "opta": "A cutting plane line", "optb": "Section lining", "optc": "Visible lines", "optd": "Lines and arrows", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These breaks are used to shorten the view of an object:", "opta": "Section breaks", "optb": "Aligned breaks", "optc": "Conventional breaks", "optd": "Full breaks", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In architectural drawing ________ are often used to illustrate and detail structural components.", "opta": "Foundation beam detail sections", "optb": "Wall sections", "optc": "Building sections", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When only a small section of an interior area needs to be revealed the drafter can use a ________ section.", "opta": "half", "optb": "quarter", "optc": "full", "optd": "broken out", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of section, one quarter of the object is removed:", "opta": "Revolved section", "optb": "Removed section", "optc": "Quarter section", "optd": "Half section", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A ________ section allows the drafter to create a Cutting Plane line which is not in a straight line across the part.", "opta": "Offset", "optb": "half", "optc": "whole", "optd": "broken out", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ________ is a standard element of a section view in a technical drawing.", "opta": "Cutting Plane line", "optb": "Section lines", "optc": "Material hatch pattern", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When creating a Cutting Plane line with AutoCAD it is customary to use a ________ to create the line.", "opta": "center line", "optb": "polyline", "optc": "dashed line", "optd": "hatch line", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is a common method for connecting steel members of buildings and bridges:", "opta": "Assembly", "optb": "Fabricating", "optc": "Riveting", "optd": "Welding", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of structural steel drawing shows all dimensions necessary for fabrication:", "opta": "Shop drawings", "optb": "Design drawings", "optc": "Weldment drawings", "optd": "Application drawings", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are joined together in the field to build a structure:", "opta": "Riveted members", "optb": "Main members", "optc": "Steel fabrications", "optd": "Assembled fabrications", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These plans, made by the steel fabricator, are assembly drawings for the steel structure:", "opta": "Welding plans", "optb": "Assembly plans", "optc": "Construction plans", "optd": "Erection plans", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This material is used in masonry construction, most commonly for ornamental facing:", "opta": "Face brick", "optb": "Clay tile", "optc": "Natural stone", "optd": "Aggregate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of weld is the most common in structural steel fabrication:", "opta": "Fillet weld", "optb": "Beam weld", "optc": "Rivet weld", "optd": "Structural weld", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In this type of concrete, the steel is pretensioned before the superimposed load is applied:", "opta": "Aggregate", "optb": "Prestressed", "optc": "Reinforced", "optd": "Preloaded", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of solid is egg-shaped and can be created by revolving an ellipse around one of its axes:", "opta": "Ellipsoid", "optb": "Torus", "optc": "Cone", "optd": "Cylinder", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some of the common terms used to describe technical drawing include:", "opta": "Drafting", "optb": "Engineering Graphics", "optc": "Engineering Drawing", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An architect often relies on a ________ to complete the set of technical drawings used in the design of an office building.", "opta": "technical illustrator", "optb": "artist", "optc": "drafter", "optd": "construction superintendent", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In oblique sketches, the most commonly used angles for receding lines are:", "opta": "15 or 30 degrees", "optb": "25 or 30 degrees", "optc": "30 or 45 degrees", "optd": "45 or 60 degrees", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A drafter who develops technical drawings of a highway overpass would most likely be a ________ drafter.", "opta": "architectural", "optb": "civil", "optc": "mechanical", "optd": "process piping", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These types of projectors converge at a vanishing point:", "opta": "Perspective", "optb": "Parallel", "optc": "Orthographic", "optd": "Oblique", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A ________ is the person responsible for verifying that the drawings in a project set are free of mistakes.", "opta": "client", "optb": "CAD trainee", "optc": "receptionist", "optd": "checker", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of solid has two bases that are parallel equal polygons:", "opta": "Pyramid", "optb": "Prism", "optc": "Cone", "optd": "Torus", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An oil refinery relies on which type of drafter to maintain and update the technical piping drawings used for the construction and maintenance of the facility.", "opta": "architectural", "optb": "civil", "optc": "process piping", "optd": "electrical", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When designing a home for a client, one of the most important pre-design considerations that an architect needs to address is ________.", "opta": "how much money the client is willing to spend.", "optb": "the site on which the house is to sit", "optc": "the nearest grocery store", "optd": "whether or not there is a curb and gutter system", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is formed where three or more surfaces intersect:", "opta": "Oblique", "optb": "Line", "optc": "Edge", "optd": "Vertex", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Department of Labor's Bureau of Labor Statistics predicts that some of the best opportunities for employment in our near future will be for students who ________.", "opta": "drop out of high school", "optb": "graduate from high school and go right into the workforce", "optc": "obtain a two year technical degree from a community or junior college", "optd": "earn a B.S. degree in psychology", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Three dimensional models are often used in the design process to ________.", "opta": "help the client understand the overall design concept", "optb": "help the client select a color for their carpet", "optc": "provide the client with a model which they can use to impress their friends", "optd": "determine the quantity of brick needed to build the house", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Students can complete an associate's degree in drafting which normally takes about ________ years to complete.", "opta": "one", "optb": "two", "optc": "three", "optd": "four", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is used in drawings to represent the edge of a solid object:", "opta": "Angle", "optb": "Vertex", "optc": "Surface", "optd": "Line", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The daily workload of a ________ drafter would generally include technical drawings of machine parts.", "opta": "architectural", "optb": "civil", "optc": "electrical", "optd": "mechanical", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of solid has a polygon for a base and triangular lateral faces that intersect at a vertex:", "opta": "Pyramid", "optb": "Prism", "optc": "Cone", "optd": "Torus", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These include taper pins, straight pins, dowel pins, clevis pins, and cotter pins:", "opta": "Bolts", "optb": "General fasteners", "optc": "Machine pins", "optd": "Rivets", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distance a screw thread advances axially in one turn is the:", "opta": "Lead", "optb": "Pitch", "optc": "Turn", "optd": "Crest", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The standard number of threads per inch for various diameters is the:", "opta": "Series of thread", "optb": "Lead", "optc": "Major diameter", "optd": "Thread pitch", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of fit is high quality and is used for the bulk of interchangeable screw thread work:", "opta": "Class 1", "optb": "Class 2", "optc": "Class 3", "optd": "Class 4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This type of thread is a thread on the inside of a member:", "opta": "Basic thread", "optb": "External thread", "optc": "Internal thread", "optd": "Major diameter thread", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the smallest diameter of a screw thread:", "opta": "Internal thread diameter", "optb": "Minor diameter", "optc": "Major diameter", "optd": "External thread diameter", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the bottom surface joining the sides of two adjacent threads:", "opta": "Lead", "optb": "Pitch", "optc": "Crest", "optd": "Root", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When lines intersect on a drawing at angles of this many degrees, it is customary not to dimension the angle:", "opta": "360", "optb": "180", "optc": "90", "optd": "45", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the term for the range of tightness or looseness resulting from the allowances and tolerances in mating parts:", "opta": "Limits", "optb": "Fit", "optc": "Specifications", "optd": "Allowance", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the measured size of a finished part:", "opta": "Actual size", "optb": "Dimensioned size", "optc": "Production size", "optd": "Basic size", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This means that a feature of a finished product contains the maximum amount of material permitted by the toleranced dimensions for that feature:", "opta": "Maximum material condition", "optb": "Machined material condition", "optc": "Maximum machined indication", "optd": "Machine mark indication", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is the theoretically exact size from which limits of size are determined:", "opta": "Actual Size", "optb": "Dimensioned size", "optc": "Production size", "optd": "Basic size", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acceptable parts must not extend beyond this:", "opta": "Boundary limits", "optb": "Hole limits", "optc": "Specification", "optd": "Tolerances", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This practice considers an individual part's dimensions and tolerances and that part's relation to its related parts:", "opta": "Applying allowances", "optb": "Geometric dimensioning and tolerancing", "optc": "Creating datum references", "optd": "Angular dimensioning tolerances", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A half-moon protractor is divided into how many degrees?", "opta": "360", "optb": "180", "optc": "270", "optd": "310", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A line drawn with a long section, short dash, and another long section is a ________.", "opta": "hidden feature", "optb": "center of a circle", "optc": "center axis of a hidden cylinder", "optd": "center of a radius", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Traditional drafters need to be able to create several different line widths because ________.", "opta": "different line widths convey different information", "optb": "the line width has to do with how dark it appear in the finished drawing", "optc": "they seem to transmit better in a fax machine", "optd": "it makes no difference", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Several of the tools used in traditional drafting include the following:", "opta": "Parallel straight edge", "optb": "45 degree triangle", "optc": "Circle template", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A civil engineer working on a bridge design would probably rely on his ________ scale for checking printed drawings.", "opta": "engineer's", "optb": "metric", "optc": "architect's", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to convert fractional inches into decimal inches ________.", "opta": "look on a metric conversion chart", "optb": "divide the numerator (top number) by the denominator (bottom number)", "optc": "check the engineer's scale", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An engineer's scale would be used to measure lines on a drawing where the scale factor reads ________.", "opta": "1/4\" = 1'-0\"", "optb": "1/8\" = 1'-0\"", "optc": "1\" = 100'", "optd": "3/4\" = 1'-0\"", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Referring to the fractional inches to decimal inches to millimeter conversion chart on page 55 what is the equivalent mm measurement of 3/16 inch.", "opta": "1.906", "optb": "4.7625", "optc": "5.958", "optd": "14.6844", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some traditional board drafters preferred the drafting machine over the parallel straight edge because it could be used without the need for________.", "opta": "circle templates", "optb": "triangles", "optc": "technical pens", "optd": "lettering guides", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The first step in creating a traditional technical drawing is to ________.", "opta": "draw a series of guide lines", "optb": "set up the miter line", "optc": "align the paper so that it will be positioned square to the parallel bar", "optd": "sharpen the leads in the technical pens", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A projection weld is a type of:", "opta": "Resistance weld", "optb": "Arc weld", "optc": "Gas weld", "optd": "Fillet weld", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These weld symbols have no arrow-side or other-side significance:", "opta": "Projection or seam weld", "optb": "Back or backing weld", "optc": "Surface or groove weld", "optd": "Flash and upset weld", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A back or backing weld is a type of:", "opta": "Groove weld", "optb": "Resistance weld", "optc": "Arc and gas weld", "optd": "Upset weld", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Welding drawings are a special type of this kind of drawing:", "opta": "Symbol", "optb": "Perspective", "optc": "Assembly", "optd": "Isometric", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is one of the basic types of welded joints:", "opta": "T-joint", "optb": "Rear joint", "optc": "Angle joint", "optd": "Groove joint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In these drawings it is necessary to show cut surfaces and distinguish between adjacent parts:", "opta": "Auxiliary drawings", "optb": "Assembly sections", "optc": "3D assemblies", "optd": "Parts lists", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These drawings are given to contractors to perform work or manufacture individual parts:", "opta": "Assembly details", "optb": "3D drawings", "optc": "Working drawings", "optd": "Skeleton assemblies", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In working drawings, these show all necessary information not given directly on the drawing with its dimensions and notes:", "opta": "Document strips", "optb": "Portable documents", "optc": "Formatting forms", "optd": "Title and record strips", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This should show what changes were made, when, and by whom:", "opta": "Portable document", "optb": "Record of revisions", "optc": "Title form", "optd": "Revision drawings", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An accurate record of changes made to released drawings is tracked via this:", "opta": "A revision block", "optb": "The basic title form", "optc": "Working drawings", "optd": "Portable documents", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an assembly section, these parts should have their section lines left out or shown solid black:", "opta": "Bolts", "optb": "All fasteners", "optc": "Thin parts", "optd": "Rivets", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "These are groups of components of a larger machine:", "opta": "Subassemblies", "optb": "External assemblies", "optc": "Component assemblies", "optd": "Major assemblies", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}